<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An armoure of proufe very profitable, as well for princes, noble men; and gentlemen, as all other in authoritie, shewing the firme fortresse of defence, and hauen of rest in these troublesome times and perilous dayes. Made by Iohn VVoolton minister of the Gospell.</title>
            <author>Woolton, John, 1535?-1594.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1576</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 159 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15700</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106615</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842328</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842328</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6973</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15700)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6973)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 583:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An armoure of proufe very profitable, as well for princes, noble men; and gentlemen, as all other in authoritie, shewing the firme fortresse of defence, and hauen of rest in these troublesome times and perilous dayes. Made by Iohn VVoolton minister of the Gospell.</title>
                  <author>Woolton, John, 1535?-1594.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 48 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [H. Bynneman for] Iohn Shepperde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1576.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kings and rulers --  Duties --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6973:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6973:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ <hi>AN ARMOVRE of Proufe: Very profitable, as well for Princes, noble men; and gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as all other in authoritie, ſhewing the firme fortreſſe of defence, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of reſt in theſe troubleſome times and perilous dayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Made by <hi>Iohn VVoolton</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpell.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of a serpent on a rod upheld by two hands emerging from clouds</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>¶ <hi>IMPRINTED AT LONDON by Iohn Shepperde. Anno.</hi> 1576.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>coat of arms of the Cecil family</figDesc>
                  <p>COR. VNVM VIA. VNA</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6973:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6973:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the right honorable, Sir VVilliam Cicil Knight, Lord Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh, and Lord high Treaſurer of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>Iohn VVoolton</hi> wiſheth the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor of God; continual health, and proſperous ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is engraffed, and deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rooted in mans minde, an <note place="margin">Man iudgeth corruptly accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of worldly mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> error and falſe opinion, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che euen immediately after his dounefall, did ſpring and ſhew it ſelfe out of originall ſinne, to iudge of Gods Prouidence according to wordly euents: and if ſometime hee ſee the better ſide, and iuſter cauſe oppreſſed fraudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently and tirarmouſly, then he eyther denyeth altogither Gods care ouer mortal men, or elſe doubteth of the equitie of the cauſe, and giueth iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that thoſe which are ouercome, haue the weaker title, and are caſt away from God, and that the conquerours and victors doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende the ſincere parte and better title, and and are accepted of God And this thing commeth to paſſe eſpecially in matters of religion, where men according to the eſtate of kingdomes, and
<pb facs="tcp:6973:3"/> inclination of the people, do weigh and eſteme <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> frutes of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ubting minde matters of eligion.</note> the truth of the ſame. I his greeuous error, if it continue any ſpace in mans breſt, it breedeth in ſome an Apoſtaſle, and vtter departing from God: In otherſome troublous motions, and flitting mindes, whiche in time do quenche in man all ſenſe of godlyneſſe, and at laſt carieth him headlong into a godleſſe contempt of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or driueth him downeright into dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſperation. For mans minde, which was
<note place="margin">gonies of the inde and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ience intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> created to ſearche out the truth and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the ſame, is not able to indure thoſe conflictes, and aſſaultes of a vexed mind: and ſorely I am of this opinion, that the gnowings and frettings of the conſcience which ariſe by meanes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, are more dolorous than any torments whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che mans body may ſuſtayne. <hi>Pompeius Magnus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">ompeyus Aagnus.</note> ariuing at <hi>Mitelenen,</hi> after that famous foughte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fielde of <hi>Pharſalie,</hi> diſcourſeth with <hi>Cratippus</hi> his whoſe race of life, and maketh large mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his aduerſe fortune, and laſtly drowned in the gulfe of deſpaire, viterly denyeth Goddes prouidence, by cauſe in a iuſt and good quarrelf (as himſelfe thought) God ſuffered him to fall.
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emades.</note> And <hi>Demades</hi> that eloquente orator and graue Senator of <hi>Greece,</hi> giuing as holeſome counſaile in matters touching the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth, as ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:6973:3"/> 
               <hi>Themistocle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Miltiades</hi> or <hi>Pericles,</hi> was wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to alledge for himſelfe, that frowarde fortune and vnhappie deſteny, did fruſtrate his deuiſes.</p>
            <p>VVhiche voyce albeit euen then it eſcaped not iuſt reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſion of the wiſe, yet it paynteth liuely vnto vs the ruine of the Attyke commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth, the greate perilles and daungers in all cinill regiment, and the declining of Empires and kingdomes. VVe liue no doubt in the laſt times, and old age of the world, which is feeble and doing, for by common eourſe of nature; after vigor and ſtrength, foloweth inclination and fayntneſſe, and tho end of things is always weake: VVherein we ſee the rage of Sathan to ſpurre mens myndes to ward furie; to ſtirre vp troubles, cruell warres, and all kind of calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties euery where, and for that he knoweth the reſtitution of mankinde to approch, and hys time ſhort, he omitteth nothing vnattempted, to drawe great ſwarmes and companies of the worlde, to forſake nuereligion, and to runne into ignorance and blaſphemy.</p>
            <p>And that I may let paſſe thoſe, that vpon the <note place="margin">Occaſions that moue wordling to relinquiſhe Religion.</note> coaſtes of Hungary depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs to the Turke perſuaded with wealth and proſperous ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of his wares: VVhat Tragedies dothe the Diuell moue on each ſide of vs to terrifie men
<pb facs="tcp:6973:4"/> from folowing Chriſt his enſigne, and from a free and liberall profeſsion of his moſt ſacred and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ernall Goſpell In <hi>Scoplande</hi> we haue heard of dayly ſlaughters and butchery of Chriſtes children, where it is now a common ſleight to miniſter an Italian dramme vnto their Princes, and trayt crouſly to murder the peeres and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of their land. The dealings of the Duke of <hi>Alu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and his ſucceſſor in the lowe countries, are more lamentable, where no lawes, no faith, no promiſes are kepte, no antiquitie of noble families regarded, no faithfull ſeruice to theyr Prince and countrie remembred, no ſilence nor abiuring of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rue religion accepted, but Spaniſhe crueltie executed uppon all ages, degrees and fexes, without any conſideration: beſides theſe, no ſpoyle nor robberie of mens ſubſtaunes, no extreame puniſhments nor torments, no raſing of townes and Cities, no adulterie nor filthy Sodomy can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent their monſtrous and moſt vile natures and appetites. All good natures tremble and quake at the reports of the French eruelty, exceeding <hi>Phar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Nero</hi> in all rage and tirannie, whoſe proceedings are ſuch, that we may gather that their determinate mindes and purpoſes are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeaſſe, vntill they haue the hart bloud of all thoſe in whom any ſparke
<pb facs="tcp:6973:4"/> or breath of Chriſtian Religion at any tyme heretofore hath hath appeared, and ſo driuing away the ſhining brightneſſe of the Goſpell, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the Romiſh Idoll, and to exalt him in all Europe, as the chiefe Monarche agayne. For now they cloke not their malice with pretence of ſuppreſsing rebellious ſubiects: but lynking vnto them the Spaniſh natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, do moſt euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly profeſſe them ſelues the ſworne enimies of Chriſte his eſpouſe, and the chiefe defenders and Champions of Babyloniſh Idolatrie. The puiſſance and greate mighte of that ſide, theyr terrible executions, and the froward euents of lawful and godly enterpriſes, languiſheth and wholly diſcourageth many men that hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue giuen ſome countenance vnto the Goſpell: And no mortall wight were able to continue in ſo ſharp and endleſſe a battel firme and conſtant, without an vndoubted aſſurance of Gods prouidence and fatherly care ouer them. VVherefore godly men comfort them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with a grounded faith, being toſſed too and fro, in vehemente ſtormes and tempeſtes, and do knowe that the ſonne of God guideth the ſterne of his ſhippe, and as hee promiſed, ſo hath he in deede exhibited his holy ſpirite, by whome hee giueth vnto his children courage
<pb facs="tcp:6973:5"/> and ſtrength, to giue teſtimonie of the trueth, without dred in the middle of all puniſhments and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Touching the fornamed Tirants, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> me God hath giuen ſtout ſtomackes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, greete victories, whereby they are grow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h into a licetious boldneſſe, bending <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ght againſt Chriſt his Church: wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> our ſelues, that God wil withdrawe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> his generall graces, that he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them of all their of n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ments in body and mind, that he wil leaue them vnto themſelues; as he forſooke <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpey, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lcibiades, Alexander</hi> and <note place="margin">VVhat end aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the enimies of the Goſpell. <hi>Valerianus.</hi>
               </note> ſuch like. VVe haue an eſpeciall example here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in <hi>Valerianus.</hi> the Emperour, who in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning for his vpright iuſtice and valiant hart, was deerely beloued of the Senate and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people, but afterward, ſetting himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods Church, became captiue vnto <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pores.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Sapores.</note> king of the Perſians, who vſed his head as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ootoſtoole, mounting vpon his horſe, and in his olde age, vnskinned him from the toppe of the head vnto the plant of the foote, ſo that at laſt he found an ouermatch ſtirred vp by God, <note place="margin">Chaldaeus Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphr. cui con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicit tamen Caluinus.</note> that taught him how tender in the ſight of the Lord are the woundes of his ſaints. Their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are prepared no doubt: albeit ſomewhat de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the ſtackneſſe thereof, wil be recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb facs="tcp:6973:5"/> with the weight of the ſame. <hi>Cayne</hi> his fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>recide was puniſhed in the ſeuenth generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Bias</hi> his opinion is noted of the wiſe, who when he ſawe a wicked monſter proſper ſay de, <hi>Aſſhredly that felow muſt needes be puniſhed, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I liue not to ſee it.</hi> The hiſtorie of <hi>Beſſus</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth herevnto, who murthered his owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <note place="margin">Plutarchus.</note> and liued long after in greate proſperitie, vntill at the laſt, paſsing by a noſt of chittering birdes as he went to a ſolemne banquet wel ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companyed in great madneſſe threw down the neſt with his ſpeare ſaying, Theſe birdes doe righte and daye with their noiſe lay vnto my charge the murther of my father whervpon he was apprehended, condemned, and executed. Let no man therfore fret bycauſe of the greene <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> bay tree in Libanus: ſtay but a little, and the leaues will fail, the tree will rotte away, and the plague thereof will no where be founde.</p>
            <p>And touching our ſelues, I ſee no cauſe why we ſhould in the quarrel of our God conceyue
<note place="margin">VVhat Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ought to do in theſe peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous dayes.</note> ſuch trernoling and feare at the great ſtrength and tyra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nie of our enimies, as many car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall men nowe do. VVhen Hieruſalem was in greate diſtreſſe and daunger of mighty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nimies, Eſay the Prophete is ſente from the Lorde with thys iniunction, <hi>In ſilence</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Eſay. 30.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:6973:6"/> 
               <hi>and in confidence ſhall bee your ſtrength.</hi> VVhat is this <hi>ſilence?</hi> and what is this <hi>confidence?</hi> Firſt it is our duetie to ſuffer afflictions patiently. Secondly, not to buſie our ſelues out of our vocation. Thirdly, not to miſtruſt Gods helpe, and ſo carnally to enter into vngodly leagues and vnlawfull friendſhips, as the kings of Iuda <note place="margin">No leagues are to be made with Gods enimies.</note> leaned ſometime vppon the Egyptians, nowe vppon the Sy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ans, and in the ende were made ſlaues vnto them, and caſt out of Gods fauour, for ſo ſpeaketh the prophete Iehu vnto Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <note place="margin">2. Para. 19.</note> 
               <hi>VVouldest thou helpe the wicked, and loue them that hate the Lorde?</hi> for this thing the wrath of the Lord is vpon thee. Agaynſte, ſuch difference and vnlawful defenſes are theſe wordes ſpoken: <hi>In ſilence and confidence ſhall be youre ſtrength:</hi> that is to ſaye, awaite vppon <note place="margin">Ieza. 30. 31. 48 Pſal. 32.</note> Gods ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, runne not to the Egyptians, Turks, Papiſts, and to haue help of them. Your cauſe is good and iuſt, the almightie regardeth you, and if you bee put to the worſe, yet is it better to ſuffer calamities, than with vnhoneſt deuiſes to hurt a good matter. Let no man faint therfore, bycauſe now adayes, many worthy men ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed with the giftes of Gods ſpirite, are Tiran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly <note place="margin">The eſtate of Chriſtes Church in this worlde.</note> murthered, by moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ile and diſhoneſt perſons. Such troubles the Church neuer wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="tcp:6973:6"/> but hath paſſed them all, and ſhall continue vntill Chriſtes comming to iudgement.</p>
            <p>The face and countenance of Gods Church is not alwayes after one maner. It is ſometime ample, faire, and glorious: ſometime ſmal, halfe darke and contemptuous in the world. Muche like the Moone, who according to hir place, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyueth from the Sunne ſundry beames, ſo
<note place="margin">The lighte of Chriſtes church neuer wholly quenched.</note> that the Diuell ſhall neuer be able vtterly to extinguiſh hir light: for euen in hir wane ſhee ſpreadeth hir out at large, and waxeth rounde and full againe. And albeit, ſome braunches of the Church be cut off and periſh, yet the roote and ſtocke of the ſame abideth alwayes ſound and vncorrupte. In the conſeruation whereof, the pleaſure of almighty. God is to excerciſe our faith, hope, and inuocation, and to giue vs to vnderſtand, that he will not permitte mans deliberations to take place in the regiment of our liues, but to acknowledge our protection to come from aboue, leaſt we might proudely boaſt <hi>Our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wne handes haue done theſe things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudi. 7.</note> If the Church be not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſerued by thoſe meanes whiche carnall reaſon deuiſeth, or at what time <note place="margin">VVhy God hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to mans policie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſes.</note> our harts do earneſtly wiſhe it, or by ſuch men who according to our iudgement, are of ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent wiſedome and ſtrength to archieue it, wee
<pb facs="tcp:6973:7"/> are euen then by vſe &amp; experience taught, that the regime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſtes congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> much va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ciuill policie. For vnto promiſes of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral bleſsings, a condition of calamitie and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction is moſt comonly annexed, wherin the beautie of Chriſts eſpouſe ſhineth moſt clere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in that ſhe beareth conſtantly and patiently for Gods cauſe, pelne, and miſerie, and at the laſt, is deliuered miraculouſly and gloriouſly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVe haue a mirror hereof, in that notable promiſe</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſmael. Iacob. Kedar. Nabayoth. Gene. 25.</note> made to Abraham and to his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie by Iſaac. <hi>In thy ſeede ſhall the nations of the earth be bleſſed,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which bleſsing Iſmael is not only excluded, but alſo caſt out and baniſhed. Yet ſurely out of Iſmael by his ſon. Kedar, that mighty nation of the Arabians often mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Scripture, did iſſue and ſpring, and from his eldeſt ſonne Nabaioth deſcended the <hi>Nahatheans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſmael and his generation with their eſtates.</note> a people in <hi>Arabia faelici,</hi> of whome the Poets ſpeake much in their monumentes, attributing vnto them the ſame name. Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met the firſt author of the Turkiſh blaſphemie, and the erector of the Saracens kingdome, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riueth his progeny by a long contract from the ſaid Iſmael, whoſe poſteritie do rule wide and broade throughout Aſia, Atricke and parte of Europ eue at this day, &amp; do not ceſſe to make continual warre with Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his children, that
<pb facs="tcp:6973:7"/> is to ſay with the true Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But Iacob the heire of the bleſsing, and hys children are ledde by and by into exile out of the <note place="margin">Iacobs condi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and of promiſe, &amp; beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth ſubiect to a ſtrange king in Egypt, where his poſteritie endured hard ſeruitude and deteſtable ſlauery many yeeres. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>au <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſau proſpereth.</hi> Gene. 36.</note> in the mean ſeaſon, enioyeth at home pleaſant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt &amp; pcace, and in plenty and wealth multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and encreaſeth that nation called Edumites. Now albeit the Iſraelites ſeeme to be abiect from god, yet they are preſerued wonderfully, &amp; moſt <note place="margin">The Iſraelites miraculouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered.</note> worthy &amp; euident tokens of Gods fauor toward them, are ſhewed in the land of Egypt, and laſtly with Gods mighty hand and ſtretched out arme, they are deliuered from Pharao his cruelty, and are reduced into their naturall countrey. God do the not therfore giue euents and ſucceſſe by ſuch meanes and wayes, nor at ſuch times as hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane reaſon craueth and deſireth: but with his long tarying, ſharpneth our faith, and kindleth an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ardent inuocation in vs, and ſo eyther mitigateth or wholly taketh away miſeries and calamities. Albeit, the ayd &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort of the holy Ghoſt doth <note place="margin">The power of the holy Ghoſt principally in torments.</note> neuer ſhew it ſelfe more manifeſtly than in aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting &amp; comforting the godly againſte the fierce and outragious torments of the wicked, whereby they are kept from deſpaire, ſtayed from deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their God, and preſerued from murmuring &amp; repining againſt his maieſtie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6973:8"/>
            <p>VVherefore let all men that haue a place in <note place="margin">The Captayne and delyueres of the Churche.</note> Chriſtes Church, reſt and ſtay them ſelues vpon God in theſe days of ours, wherin the world run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vpon wheeles: let them ſet before their eies, that <note place="margin">Dani. 12.</note> which is written in Daniel, <hi>At that tyme ſhal Michael ſtande vp the greate Prince, which ſtandeth for the children of thy people.</hi> And agayne, <hi>There is</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dani. 10.</note> 
               <hi>none that boldeth with mee, but Michael youre Prince.</hi> Theſe ſweete &amp; heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolations, are the only refuge &amp; chiefe pillers of the godly, and their whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence is repoſed vpon the Lord of hoſts, the ſon of the liuing God, who nameth himſelf the Emperour and Captaine of his Army<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and is indeed that great prince Michael, who war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth and wardeth his owne people, preſerueth his eſpouſe in ſtormes and tempeſtes, giueth hir <hi>Halcions</hi> dayes to hatch hir yong ones, repreſſeth and bride leth the furor and rage of Tyrants.</p>
            <p>The remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of theſe things as they are meete for all the members of Chriſtes Churche, ſo are they moſt neceſſary for princes and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, beeing the nourcing fathers thereof, the keepers of the two Tables, and the defenders of <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 paragraph">
                     <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> his holy word the Goſpel, agaynſt whom Sathan &amp; his limmes do rage and rore with a wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfull furie, enuying their proſperitie, vndermining their eſtate, and thirſting after their bloud &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. VVher by I haue bin moued to drawe
<pb facs="tcp:6973:8"/> thys little treatiſe, being indeed nothing elſe but a Conſolation for Princes and noble men againſt the ſubtile practiſes &amp; bloudy purpoſes of cruel tirants. This argument ſurely was moſt meet for a wiſe and profounde learned man to labour in. And I hartily wiſh, that ſome excellent wit, vpon the viewe of this my rude (but ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g foundation) might be moued to make ſome more beautifull building. In the meane ſeaſon, vntil ſome better artificer take this worke in hand, I thought good to publiſh this commonefaction or inſtruction, which I moſt humbly offer &amp; preſent vnto your right honorable Lordſhip, not as a matter need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to put you in remembrance of any thing that ſhould be wanting in your honor apperteyning to the dutie of a wiſe counſeller and iuſt magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, but rather to be as glaſſe for you to ſee and behold, to youre great comfort, howe God hath by his mighty hand always kepte and defended all ſuch Princes, Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſellers and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, as haue adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced his glory in ſetting forth true religion, and executed iuſtice in their voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and callings, wherin with what great ſtudy &amp; care of minde you honor hath labored nowe many yeeres, God &amp; good men can tell &amp; are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident witneſſe, &amp; your ſelf recording the diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh deuiſes of your enimies to thwart and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate your proceedings, to preiudice your pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb facs="tcp:6973:9"/> policies, and to bring youre honor to vtter ruine and deſtruction and on the other ſide, how God of his greate goodneſſe hath giuen good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uents to all your enterpriſes, and preſerued youre honor from tyme to time, euen miraculouſly in great perilles and dangers, muſt needes acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge Gods gracious fauor (and that I may ſo ſpeake) his approued and vnperceable armor, wherwith he ſuccoureth and ſaueth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> iudges and magiſtrates that are learned in his lawe, kiſſe his ſon Chriſt and become foſters and nourcing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of hys Spouſe the Church.</p>
            <p>The liuing God preſerue your right honorable Lordſhip from all euill, conſerue and keepe you vnto the ende in the knowen truth, defende you with his mighty hande againſte Sathans rage and furie: and finally, ſuffer you not to be diſcouraged with theſe greeuous temptations and daungers, whiche muſt needes without his ayde, not onely trouble, but alſo vtterly diſcomfort you in your calling in theſe Tragical times, wherein the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel bendeth and brandeſheth his frie dartes with greatrage, &amp; terror againſt the magiſtrates breſts. But comfort you, make your yoke pleaſant and your burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> light through the word of truth and grace of his holy Spirit, Amen From Exceter, the laſt of Febru. <hi>Anno Domini.</hi> 1576.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honors moſt humble Iohn Woolton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:6973:9"/>
            <p> AT what tyme <hi>Aurelianus</hi> the <note place="margin">Flauius Vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſcus in Aureliano. Sabellie. ennead. 7. li. 8.</note> Emperour, that obſtinate enemy to right Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the only author of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ninth rufull perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on agaynſt the Chriſtians, was much moleſted with conſpiracies and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in ſundry his Prouinces: hee appointed one <hi>Saturninus</hi> his Liefetenant in the Eaſte <note place="margin">Saturninus</note> partes: Whom the inhabitantes of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria</hi> for his approoued prowes in warre, his wiſedome and politique regiment in peace, ſaluted and proclaimed Emperour after <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relianus</hi> death. Which title and dignitie <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turninus</hi> ſo long and earneſtly refuſed, that the rude people (whom the auntient Prouerbe truly termeth a monſter of many heades) alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in a moment their louing affection into fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and of faithful frends became almoſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal foes. For they ſeeing their good willes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſidered, and all prouident care ouer them vtterly neglected, with an vniuerſall and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous noyſe, cryed <hi>kyll him, kyll him,</hi> and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:6973:10"/> their weapons threatened preſente death. <hi>Saturninus</hi> thus preſſed, or rather op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, yeeldeth vnto them: hee aſſumeth the Scepter and Dyademe, but ſpeaketh vnto them in thys wyſe. You knowe not (my deare <note place="margin">The care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully lyfe of princes &amp; noble men.</note> and louyng companions) the combe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and daungerous conditions of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and noble men, ſwoordes and pykes han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging ouer their heades, lauelins and dartes euerywhere, their heades vntruſtie, their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers faythleſſe, theyr meales carefull, their ſleepes vnquiet, their iourneys troubleſome, their expeditions vnlucky, their warres blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, their lyfe and yeares diſcommended. In youth they are thought ſelfewill: in age men ſay they dote. You now cary mee into moſte perilous and raging ſeas, but this is my only ſolace and comforte, that I ſhal not make ſhipwracke alone.</p>
            <p>Hee ſawe right well by daily experience, that menne guyding the ſterne of common wealthes, doe taſte in that courſe and trade of lyfe more Aloes than ſugre: and do ſuppe vp rather the bitterneſſe of gaules, than the ſweeteneſſe of honey. For albeit in delicate and riotous fare, in ſumptuous and gorge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous apparell they abounde and exceede, yet
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:6973:10"/> they haue in the middle of a thouſand rockes and quickeſandes, as ſnares, poyſonynges, <note place="margin">Seneca con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſiariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lib. 7.</note> conſpiracyes, Rebellions, ſodayne murders and ſuch lyke. And that I maye omittethe open wayes and moſt playne paſſages, which all men generallye treade towarde death, and the manifolde caſualties and miſchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <note place="margin">Mans lyfe fyckle and bariable.</note> wherein this ſeelye lyfe of ours is intrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped at noonedaye, whileſt wee all are borne but after one maner, and dye after a thouſand: yet eſpecially, the great men of this world do for the moſte parte ſaile in the thicke miſt, and darke night, and ſodenlye are ſtriken vnder water themſelues in a ſounde and heauye ſleepe. The ſtorme and tempeſt ſhewetlrſome tokens before it aryſeth to the vigilant huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, and Shipman. The houſes tracke before they fall. The ſmoke ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the flame folowing. Onlye without <note place="margin">Seneca e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſto. 17 epiſt. 104.</note> any watchworde man deſtroyeth man. And eſpecially the great and mightie man is ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte to the malicious and enuyous ſtroke of man: and the nerer the ſtroke the more cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is it kepte. Princes and noble men are moſt of all other deceyued by ſuch as looke cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">The noble mans lyfe moſt vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</note> vppon them, that come humbly to kiſſe their hands &amp; feete w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Al hail, ſhewing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:6973:11"/> of louing men, but hauing the inwarde appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites <note place="margin">Flatterers no ſmal de cay to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men.</note> and deſires of tauening beaſtes. <hi>Caeſar</hi> whom neither the ſtoute Germayne, the bolde Britayne, the hautie Spaniarde, the politike Frenchman, neither ſubtile Egyptian, with warlike weapons were euer able to vanquiſh in the plaine field, could not auoyd in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate at Rome, in tyme of peace, the ſhort dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of ſuch faithleſſe friendes.</p>
            <p>And that I may omit thoſe common ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, that true faith and conſtant promiſes can not ſettle themſelues about high eſtates: The deuil himſelfe, when hee ſpyeth the weapons and wittes of wicked men blunt and dull in ſuch eaſes as hee hath bin an inſatiable murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer from the beginning, ſo then doth bee prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe all his olde policies, and attempteth all meanes to caſt downe the Magiſtrates, and with them to ouerthrowe the whole multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. And that thoſe things are moſte true, many woorthye wightes haue approued and confeſſed, who ſtudying to apply all their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuours <note place="margin">Manye woorthy men heereof purpoſe refuſed publique Regument</note> with commendation and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to execute their callinges, haue ſeene good meanings and deuiſes for the moſt part turned vpſide downe. Theſe things cauſed <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> the Emperour often to call Regiment
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6973:11"/> a monſtrous beaſt. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Pompeius Magnus</hi> was aduertiſed by letters ſent vnto him from <note place="margin">Pompeius magnus.</note> the Senate, that all power and authoritie was conferred from <hi>Scylla</hi> vnto him by the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall conſent of the people, hee ſorowfully ſmit him ſelfe vppon the breaſt, ſaying thus: Ah troubles and ſorowes without end.</p>
            <p>Had it not bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>better for mee to haue diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of obſcure parentes, than thus to bee wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with publyke cares, to bee vndermined with malice and Enuie, and euer to bee a ſtraunger not only in my owne houſe, but to my deare and louing wife and children? Of <hi>Pompey</hi> his iudgement haue byn many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent men: who being delited with the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and quiet life, and wearied with weighty offices in the common wealth, haue moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly reſigned and giuen vp their authoritie. It is written of <hi>Diocletianus Auguſtus,</hi> that
<note place="margin">Diocletian.</note> of his own electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he left his dignitie, &amp; refuſed his Crowne, willing to paſſe his latter dayes rather in ſome ſolitarie place in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a Palace in the eye (as it were) of a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Empire. I am not ignoraunt what ſome Authors reporte of that facte of <hi>Diocletianus:</hi> but howſoeuer it was, it ſwarueth not from this purpoſe. <hi>Dyon</hi> in the lyfe of <hi>Adrian</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:6973:12"/> mention of one <hi>Similis,</hi> who often vſed <note place="margin">Similis.</note> to ſaye that hee accompted that priuate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of his which he lead in <hi>Campania</hi> to be his lyfe: but theſe other dayes ſpent in Court be called death and not lyfe. For ſo ſoundeth that Epitaphe which hee willed to bee ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vpon his Tombe. <hi>Here lyeth Similis whoſe name was auntient, but in deede he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued only ſeuen yeares.</hi> The noble man made ſo ſmall accompt of that his tyme ſpente in preaſe of mightie men, himſelfe the chiefe in all honour and dignitie. <hi>Xenophon</hi> in that dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue intituled <hi>Tyrannus,</hi> ſeemeth of purpoſe to induce <hi>Hiero</hi> diſputing with <hi>Socrates,</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <note place="margin">Hiero.</note> repeting and confirming by his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience the priuate and meane eſtate of lyfe: farre to excell the publique callyng of offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and the high condition of noble menne: not only in tranquillitie of mynde and eaſe of bodie: but oftentymes in competent and laudable wealth and riches.</p>
            <p>All theſe wiſe men did well perceiue that to exploite weightie affayres, and to guyde the common wealth, is a matter of much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, enwrapped aboue all other kyndes of lyfe in infinite perilles and moſt deſperate and daungerous troubles. The Emperours of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6973:12"/> 
               <hi>Rome</hi> haue well confirmed theſe things, for of fourtie of them nexte ſucceeding <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> ſcarce ten dyed naturally in their beddes. And ſo much did men ſhunne that calling, the end whereof by experience they often did ſee to be eyther the pierſing ſwoorde, or priuie poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that by coaction or conſtraint they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed the office. And in theſe our tymes, beyng no doubte the laſte and yron age of the worlde, wherein all liuing thinges in ſtrength and might doe decaye, the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and earth growne olde, and in force and power ſpent, and (as it were) worne out, what other thinges ſee wee than iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (according to the worde of Chriſt) to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde, and eſpecially diſobedience in all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees almoſte to ſuperabounde? The late <note place="margin">Vide Sera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouem &amp; Enceliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de vi &amp; natura Adamantis</note> conſpiracies, tumultes and vprores in thys our natyue countrey: and the harde harte of Adamante not poſſible to be mollifyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bloude, hath openly diſplayde a I coceneſſe in diſcipline, an obliuion of loyaltie, &amp; a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruous contempt of a moſte mylde mothers meekeneſſe and mercy. Sathan hath ſpitte out his poyſon agaynſt the prince and magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, he hath diſcharged his great ordinance againſt the Caſtle of peace and concord. The
<pb facs="tcp:6973:13"/> ſedulitie and great care of the magiſtrate hath not wanted in watching and warding the ſame: but vnleſſe the lord of heauen and earth had kept this forte, all the keepers had watched in vayne. If he had not bin on our ſyde, then <note place="margin">Pſa. 127. 124 Pſa. 143.</note> (as the Prophet ſayth) had we bin ſwallowed vp quicke: Then had the ſwelling waters gone ouer-our ſoule, and we lyke to them that goe-downe into the Pitte.</p>
            <p>Theſe things deepely weighed, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times conſidered of the noble (for they ought neuer to be forgotten) admoniſheth them not only to bee thankefull to God for ſo miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<note place="margin">Pſal. 124.</note> a deliuerance, who hath not giuen them as a pray vnto their enimies teeth: but more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer teacheth them what protection &amp; defence they ought principally to prouide hereafter in ſembable tumults and troubles. The Heathen Magiſtrate would accompt his chiefe ſuertie and beſt defence, to conſiſt in ſtore of money, in great horſes, in valiant Souldiers, in great and mightie armies. The Chriſtian Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate wil not refuſe theſe externall helpes, but principallye will acknowledge his defents to come from God, &amp; therefore will not feare <note place="margin">Pſal. 27. &amp; 117.</note> what man may doe vnto him. The Heathen Magiſtrate would make fliſh his right hande
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6973:13"/> and comforte. The Chriſtian Magiſtrate wil lift vp his eyes vnto the mountaynes, &amp; make <note place="margin">Iere. 7. Pſal. 121. Pſal. 119.</note> the Lorde his ayde and helpe, and will ſeeke his conſolation out of Gods worde. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible and preſent conſolation, and the firme <note place="margin">The diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this booke.</note> fortreſſe of chriſtian Princes and Magiſtrates conſiſteth vpon foute principall pyllers. Firſt of his vocation and callyng. Secondlye, of the worthie and moſte notable promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God in the ſcripture, that hee wil bee their helper and defendour. Thirdly, of the honour and obedience, which God ſeuerely commaundeth to be giuen vnto magiſtrates. Fourthlye, of innumerable examples in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye write: whereby wee ſee the good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates alwayes to haue bin mayntayned and preſerued, and the rebellious and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bediente to haue bin ſuppreſſed and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ <hi>The firſt Conſolation of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate in reſpecte of his calling, and of the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie thereof.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb facs="tcp:6973:14"/>
               <p>The Magiſtrate is a perſon ordeyned and <note place="margin">The defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of a Magiſtrat</note> inſtituted of God himſelfe, both to bee a maynteyner and defendour of the firſte Table, wherein thoſe thynges are eſpecially comprehended, whiche appertaine to the worſhipping of God: and alſo to be a keeper and preſeruer of the ſecond Table, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning externall diſciplyne, and obedience in humane ſocietie: and to be gods Liefetenant, ſounding the voyce of the lawe Morall, guy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his ſubiectes according to the ſame. And as this ordinance is of God: ſo hath it byn of <note place="margin">The cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a magiſtrate moſt aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. <hi>Gene. 9.</hi>
                  </note> moſt auntient tyme. For in <hi>Noha</hi> his dayes immediatly after the floud when God gaue leaue to mortall men to kill liuing creatures for their foode and ſuſtentation, he forbad them to eate beaſtes being yet aliue in their bloud, as Wolues deuour lambes, and as the Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon renteth doues, leaſt men abuſing ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertie,
<note place="margin">Pitie and mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable creatures.</note> might in tyme being fleſhed (as it wer) in crueltie, kill one another, and ſhead mannes bloud. The liuing Lorde requireth a kinde of pittie and mercy towards creatures, albeit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable: not to deale with them as with inſenſible things: wherein <hi>Cato Cenſorius</hi> is iuſtly
<note place="margin">Plutarchus in vita Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonis.</note> reprehended of <hi>Plutarch,</hi> who without all humanitie ſolde his bondmen, now olde
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6973:14"/> and altogither waſted in his ſeruice. God therefore thundereth a ſeuere intermination or threatning, ſaying, whoſo ſheadeth mannes bloud, by man ſhall his bloud be ſhead. For in the Image of God hath he made man. In which wordes of the Lord we ſee the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Magiſtrate, to the end he ſhould ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and defend the poore and innocent from iniurie and vyolence, and correct and puniſh the tranſgreſſours for their faults and offences. In tymes paſte, Kings and rulers therefore <note place="margin">The wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie ſtile of princes.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering not only the antiquitie, but alſo the dignitie of their calling to be of God, haue in their ſtiles vſed this Phraſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>N. By the grace of God King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Acknowledging that all preeminencye of <note place="margin">Pſa. 82.</note> Maieſtie, aucthoritie, and power of Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, Kings, Princes, and of all other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and officers whatſoeuer are giuen and conferred by God himſelfe. Which cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is verye profitable, not onlie to repreſſe <note place="margin">Meanes whereby mightie my are ſtayed, from arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie.</note> the inſolencie and hautineſſe of mynde, which commonly accompanieth dignitie and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, being very pernitious in all regiment: but alſo much furthereth to the better admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration and diſcharge of their calling in the feare of God. For as they ſee and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb facs="tcp:6973:15"/> themſelues appointed in their places and degrees by God: euen ſo are they ſeriouſly put in mynd that they muſt yelde an accompte of all their doings to him: and therefore they will endeuour with all their power &amp; ſtrength to obey and ſerue him with all feare and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, according to the ſaying of the King and Prophet: <hi>Be wiſe now therefore yee Kings, be learned ye iudges of the earth. Serue the Lord in feare, and reioyce in trembling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as we learne the worthineſſe of this <note place="margin">The great eſtimation of magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Heathen.</note> calling by the light of Gods worde: ſo may we ſee the ſame in the Gentiles, folowing the light of moſt woorthie titles and names: as the <hi>Perſians</hi> who both called their Kings Gods, and lying proſtrate before them, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified an opynion of their royall myndes and maieſtie. Afterward the <hi>Grecians</hi> excelling in all ſcience and learning, called their Princes Paſtors or feeders of the people: with which name excellent <hi>Homere</hi> hath celebrated woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie <hi>Agamemnon. Mynander</hi> aptly and briefly calleth a King <hi>The liuely Image of God.</hi> Albeit that ſaying ſeemeth to bee drawen out of <hi>Heſiodus</hi> an auntient Poet, who numbred noble &amp; vertouns Princes amongſt the Gods, attributing vnto them after this life a kinde of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6973:15"/> diuine power ouer men. Which opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion was afterward receiued both of the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> and <hi>Romaines:</hi> as it is moſt euident to them that obſcrue their languages. For as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Romaines</hi> all ſuch as were tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated for their noble actes, amongſt the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Gods, were called <hi>Indigetes,</hi> as if you woulde ſaye: dwellyng with the Gods. So the <hi>Athenienſians</hi> named ſuche worthie wightes <hi>Iupiters,</hi> ſonnes of God, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> heauen as it were by right of inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. But in proces of tyme, the <hi>Romaynes</hi> moſt honorably termed their Emperours and nobles, <hi>Fathers of their countrey,</hi> and added the names of <hi>Royaltie</hi> and <hi>Maieſtie.</hi> And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, accompting ſuch ſpeeches not anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their great enterpriſes and exploits, they erected vnto them Images, Altars, Chappels, Churches, Holidayes, and Sacrifices. Which doings if you trie by the touchſtone of true religion, I confeſſe they will appeare droſſe, and be founde blame woorthy. Yet I ſay, by ſome ſparke or glimſe of nature, or by ſome celeſtial inſpiration, they reuerenced nexte and immediatly vnder God the creator of things, and ſomdeale adored the Magiſtrates. Theſe examples muſt needes pleaſe all ſache as doe
<pb facs="tcp:6973:16"/> not barbarouſly reiecte the light of naturr, and the Ladie of man, Reaſon (I meane) and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</p>
               <p>But moſt pithie perſwaſions &amp; comfortable <note place="margin">Chriſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lureth the office of a magiſtrate</note> conſolations are drawen out of the welles of liuing water, not only quencting mens drye and thirſtie affections in this lyte, but ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to life euerlaſting. Almightie God ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the regiment and policie of his owne people the Iſraelites, after their entrance into the lande of Promiſe, firſt appoynted Iudges, and then Kinges, vnto whome hee made the common people ſubiecte, which authoritie and ſecular power of Magiſtrates Chriſt him ſelfe and the Apoſtles haue allowed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed. The anſwere of Chriſt touching pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Tribute, euen to a Heathen Magiſtrate is moſt euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. <hi>Giue</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to Caeſar thoſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>things that belong to Caeſar: and vnto God thoſe things that belong to God.</hi> Which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte Chriſt himſelfe fulfilled in paying Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute. The bleſſed mother of Chriſt Marie the <note place="margin">Math. 17.</note> virgine accompanied with <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> wente to <hi>Bethleem</hi> to bee taxed among other Citizens and ſubiectes. The ſpeeche of Chriſt to one of <note place="margin">Luk. 2.</note> his company caryeth weight with it: <hi>Put vppe thy ſwoorde in his place,</hi> for all that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6973:16"/> take the ſwoord, ſhall perith with the ſwoord. <note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> In which ſentence wee ſee the power of the Secular ſwoorde allowed, hauyng an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed vnto it ordinarye and lawfull cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and puniſhment, whereby priuate murders and other offences may be ſtayde and letted. It followeth then of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, that thys condition of lyfe, is bolye and acceptable to God, whereby the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient are brideled, and the innocent mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned and conſerued. Sainte <hi>Paul</hi> the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen veſſell, enlargeth and expoundeth the <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> wordes of hys maiſter: Let euery ſoule be ſubiecte vnto the highe powers: for there is no power but of God: and the powers that bee, are ordeyned of God. Whoſoeuer therefore reſiſteth the power, reſiſtech the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaunce of God: and they that reſiſt ſhall receyue to them ſelues iudgement: for Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are not to bee feared for good workes but for euill. Wilt thou then bee without feare of the power? doe will, and ſo ſhalte thou haue prayſe of the ſame, for hee is the miniſter of God for thy wealth, but if thou doe euill, feare, for he beareth not the ſwoord for naught: for he is the miniſter of god to take vengeance on him that doeth euill. Wherefore you muſt
<pb facs="tcp:6973:17"/> be ſubiect not bicauſe of wrath onlye, but alſo for conſcience ſake. For for this cauſe ye pay alſo Tribute, for they are Gods miniſters, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying themſelues for the ſame thing. In this place the holie ghoſt calleth three tymes the Magiſtrate by the name of Gods miniſter. And is not this a true, a ſtedfaſt, and an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent comforte? Is not the great and heauie burden of Magiſtrates made lighte? Is not their penſiue myndes and carefull care eaſed and relieued?</p>
               <p>In tymes of darkneſſe none were thought <note place="margin">A magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting his calling doth God good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</note> to ſerue God, but ſuch as went into the church to heare mattins and maſſe. But S. <hi>Paul</hi> the organe and inſtrument of God, tracheth that a Magiſtrate ſitting in iudgement, hearing pleas, examining cauſes, ſuccoring the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and orphane, and pronouncing ſentence according to iuſtice and equitie, doeth God true and faithfull ſeruice. Wherefore albeit many griefes, cares, ſorrowes, calamities, and incommodities doe accomber this lyfe, doe waſte and conſume them, yet haue they this conſolation: I execute this my condition and eſtate by Gods ordinance and calling, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther therefore God prolong or ſhorten my dayes, it forceth not. I lyue and dye in that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6973:17"/> function whiche is acceptable vnto God. And <note place="margin">God direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces hart.</note> God ſurely doth not onely gouerne their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall doings, but boweth &amp; inclineth theyr harts and deniſes after his will and pleaſure, according to the ſaying of the moſt prudente <hi>Salomon,</hi> The Kings hart is in the hande of <note place="margin">Prou. 21.</note> the Lord, as the riuers of water, he turneth it whether ſoeuer it pleaſeth him. Thus you ſee with what waightie words the ſpirit of God extolleth their callings, and that not withoute brgent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. For if we take away the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, or wilfully violate their ſacred au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, we take the ſunne out of the world, we abandon truth and peace, we make the whole earth a denne of theeues.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. 2. <hi>The ſeconde conſolation, drawen from Gods manifolde promiſes, to help and defende the Magiſtrate.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IF Princes or Magiſtrates dyd turmoyle and tumble in their <note place="margin">Gods eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ouer the Prince and Magiſtrate.</note> regiment without Gods ſpeciall help and prouidence, no maruell it were, if the thought and care
<pb facs="tcp:6973:18"/> of one day, did vtterly ouerwhelme and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them. But therefore haue they an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable ſolace, that God both conferreth do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and rule at his owne pleaſure, and alſo directeth and guideth them accordingly, vſing them only as externall inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. And his exceeding greate loue is moſt euident to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them, in that to euery Magiſtrate and
<note place="margin">God by hys holy Angels, defendeth the magiſtrates. <hi>Dan. 10. &amp;. 12.</hi>
               </note> Prince in their dominions, be appointeth ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Angels to defende, ſtrengthen, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them. Wherof we haue an example in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> where mention is made, that the Angell <hi>Michaell</hi> ſloode on the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſide againſt their enimies. It were impertinent to this matter, to alledge mens opinions of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, wherin there is ſome diuerſitie. But this is truely gathered, that as the wicked fiende <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> ſendeth legions of Diuels into Princes palaces to ſtirre vp ſeditions, and to bring in al kind of calamities: ſo Gods An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel pitcheth his camp round about them, and if they feare God, they haue always more nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber with them than againſt them, to ſhield the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the darts of Sathans Souldiers, and to bridle their malice and furie.</p>
            <p>The Philoſophers, into whom nature pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red viuacitie and ſharpneſſe of wit, did ſee that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6973:18"/> monarchies and kingdoms could not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue <note place="margin">The manner of the olde world, in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</note> by humane policie, &amp; were conſtreyned to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feffe, that by Gods prouidence kings &amp; king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> maintained &amp; defended. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the firſt age amongſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gentiles, vſed firſt before they wente to the Eloction of their prince, to offer ſacrifice to their gods, &amp; crownd him King, who by Oracle was pronounced moſt meete to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office, wherein they haue ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their minds in this matter: verily y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out gods help, they are able to accompliſh no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing agayn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> through his help, they are able to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Somnius</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Philo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pher <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Egypt bet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> how Great: <hi>Alexander</hi> went to off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnto Iupiter of <hi>Ammo</hi> in <hi>Egipt,</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> naturlled) he anſwered wel, That al men were vndor Gods hand and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Speciall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</note> poyce but to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he) and to be a prince, is the higheſt and greanſt benefite. He added moreouer: that God was a parent ginerally vnto al me, but that he eſpecially a dopted vnto himſelf as his moſt louing childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> princes &amp; mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rats: And certen it is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many, who haue him caſt out by the it parentes or kinſſblke, as it were an vntimely fruite, haue vin by Gods ſingular prouidence preſerued, yea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing obiected to Beaſtes, haue bin of buite
<pb facs="tcp:6973:19"/> beaſtes nouriſhed, and at laſt became greate Princes, and Lords of the world. We reade in hiſtories, that <hi>Romulus</hi> was nouriſhed of a Woolfe: <hi>Cyrus</hi> of a Bitche: <hi>Abidus</hi> of a Doe: <hi>Hiero</hi> of Bees, that broughte hony into hys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppes. And finally, that I may not omit king <hi>Dauid,</hi> who in his yong yeeres was a refuſe among his brethren in his fathers houſe: how wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derfully was he preferued from the mouth of the Lion and Beare: howe miraenlouſly was the yong Babe <hi>Moſes</hi> taken out of the deepe waters, and appointed to leade the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell through the redde Sea. Such enſamples bothe prophane and diuine, (if they are to be called prophane, that miniſter ſo good matter,) do playnely declare, that ſuch as are ordeyned to be Princes and Rulers, are euen from the houre of their virth, receyned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods Iutele and protection.</p>
            <p>The ſumme and effect thereof conſifleth in this, that the Magiſtrate haue onely and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes before his eyes, Gods prouidence and mercy in his ſonne Chriſt: ſo ſhall he and all his buſineſſe, be farre from perill and daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ſafely ſtand without all compaſſe of gunſhot. Let him remember Gods earneſt promiſe to the Iſraelites, obeying his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6973:19"/> 
               <hi>If thou hearken vnto my</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 23.</note> 
               <hi>voyce, and do all that I ſpeake, then I will bee an enimie vnto thy enimies, and will afflicte them that afflict thee.</hi> If hee feare God in <note place="margin">The Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that ſetteth God before hys eyes, cannot periſh.</note> deede, this notable promiſe will more encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage him, than all Caſtles, Towres, muniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Armies. For if God will be an eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie vnto their enimies, let their aduerſaries deuiſe, imagine, conſpire, and bend all force a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Magiſtrate, they cannot preuayle, they cannot vndermine or ſupplant them, ſo long as God defendeth the Magiſtrate, and fighteth againſt their enimies. How is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that the one ſhoulde preuayle, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther periſh? <hi>Dauid</hi> hauing approoued the trueth of Gods promiſe in him ſelfe, farre aboue hys expectation, vttereth this ſentence: I wil loue <note place="margin">Pſal. 18.</note> thee deerely O Lord my ſtrength: The Lord is my rocke and my fortreſſe, and he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuereth me, my God and my ſtrength, in him will I truſt, my ſhielde, the horne alſo of my ſaluation, and my refuge. And agayne: Thou diddeſt cauſe thy Iudgemente to bee <note place="margin">Pſal. 76.</note> heard from Heauen, therefore the Earthe fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and was ſtill. When thou O God aroſe to iudgement to all the meeke of the worlde. The worthy Captayne <hi>Ioſua</hi> called to ruls
<pb facs="tcp:6973:20"/> and conduct <hi>Iſrael</hi> into the lande of Promis, receyueth moſt heauenly encouragements at <note place="margin">Ioſu. 1.</note> Gods mouth, ſpeaking vnto him in this wiſe: There ſhall not be a man able to withſtande thee all the dayes of thy lyfe. Is I was with <note place="margin">The Prince and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate ought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ead Gods booke.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> ſo wil I he with thee, I wil not leaue nor forſake thee. Let not this Booke of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> law departe out of thy mouth, but meditate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in day and night. Haue not I commounded thee to be ſtrong and of a good courage? feare not, for I the Lord thy God will be wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thee whetherſoeuer thou goeſt. Theſe wordes are mightie and ardent, which all Princes &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ought to apprebende and bolde faſt. They were withoute doubt written to thys ende, that all ſuch as continue in Gods feare, might knowe wherevnto to truſt. For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer things are written afore time, are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for our learning, that wee through paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and comforte of the Scriptures myghte haue hope. Whenſoeuer then, any Prince or Magiſtrate will make Gods word his chiefe ſolace and treaſure, will loue and feare God, and truſt in his grace and mercie: he ſhall haue God his righte arnre, his buckler and ſhield, his patrone and defender, that: bee may quietly and ſafely lay him downe to ſleepe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6973:20"/> and take his reſt, for that the Lorde of heauen <note place="margin">Pſal. 4.</note> and earth ſuſteyneth him. And therein obſerue and diligently recorde the often repetition of theſe wordes, <hi>Be ſtrong, and of good courage.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Courage and boldneſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable in Princes.</note> If he had bin a milkeſoppe and faint harted in his office, he coulde not haue ſerued God, nor executed his calling, nor prouided for hys army. This example, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mightie would fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, they ſhuld not be ſo eaſily co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, they ſhoulde not hazarde and make ſhipwracke of their fame, honor, and dignitie.</p>
            <p>We ſee worldly Princes onely or princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to depende vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their wiſedome, ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth,
<note place="margin">The chiefe comfort of carnal Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> and riches (ignorant as it ſhould appeare, that all Potentates are by Gods Prouidence ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aunced and ſet vp, and by his hand diſplaced and pulled downe) For preferment is neyther from the Eaſt nor from the Weſt, nor from the South: but God is the Iudge, he maketh <note place="margin">Pſal. 75.</note> lowe, and be maketh high. Such men there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leaning to ſuche brittle and weake poſts, are wounded vppon the ſplinters and ſhiuers, their fall and ruine is greate, their ſhame and ignomie is greater, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> triu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ph of their enimies is greateſt of all.</p>
            <p>That noble and Godly Prince <hi>Dauid,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dauid.</note> may be liuely example and ſpectacle vnto
<pb facs="tcp:6973:21"/> all Chriſtian Magiſtrates. For being rich and mightie, yet hee accoumpted the promiſes of the Lorde, and confidence in the liuing God to be his principall Armory. The ſaluation of <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> the righteous men ſhal be of the Lord: he ſhal be their help in time of trouble, for the Lorde ſhall help them and deliuer them: he ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer them from the wicked, and ſhall ſaue them, bycauſe they truſt in him. And agayne, at ſuch time as he was to be annoynted King, and to aſſume that great office and charge, he comforteth him ſelfe in the holy Ghoſt after this manner. The Lord is my light and my <note place="margin">Pſal. 27.</note> ſaluation, whome ſhall I feare? the Lorde is the ſtrength of my life, of whome ſhall I bee afrayde? When the wicked, euen my enimies and my foes came vpon me to eate my fleſhe, they ſtumbled and fell. Though an hoſt pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched agaynſt me, mine hart ſhoulde not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayd Though warre be raiſed agaynſt mee, I will truſt in this. One thing haue I deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Lord, that I will require, euen that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lorde all the dayes of my life, to beholde the beauti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Lord, and to viſite his temple. For in the time of trouble he ſhal hide me in his Tabernacle, in the ſecret place of his Pauilion ſhall he hide
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6973:21"/> me, and ſet me vpon a Rocke. What neede many authorities in ſo cleare a caſe? You ſee euidently, that God withſtandeth and reſiſteth the moſt puiſſant and fierce enimies of hys Magiſtrates, that he promiſeth to coole theyr courage, to mitigate their madneſſe, and to repreſſe their rage. Agayn, that what commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie and ornament ſoeuer may beautifie their calling: God giueth and graunteth farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue their expectation.</p>
            <p>Which wondeful loue and mercie of God, <note place="margin">The miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ende of ſuch as haue not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged theyr power from God.</note> for that ſome <hi>Nemroth,</hi> and mightie men of this worlde, being as it were drunken with their ſo proſperous ſucceſſes, haue not aknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, they haue at the laſt bin made ſeruile ſlaues, too obiect, and cruel raſcalles: and being a little before baughty as Lions, haue bin for their vnthankfulneſſe throwne downe, theyr honor layd in the duſt: and them ſelues haue layne in the way like dead Dogges. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore theſe conſiderations ought alwayes to be in the eyes and mindes of Princes and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, that they may feare and reuerence God, and repoſe their confidence rather in his maieſtie, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in outward power &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth. For to what purpoſe are expert Captaynes and Souldiers, Irmies well ordered, ſtore of
<pb facs="tcp:6973:22"/> all munition, plentie of victuall. Are not all theſe loſt in a momente? and euen as wee doe cut downe greene graſſe, ſo the God of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confoundeth all the glorie of warre &amp; of bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell. What a huge power had <hi>Holofernes</hi> at <note place="margin">We ought not to truſtin ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth. <hi>Iudeth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; 7</hi> Leagues and truces with wicked and godleſſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces haue euill euentes.</note> the ſeege of <hi>Bethulia,</hi> what policie and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle was vſed to ſtoppe the water from them, ſo to inforce them to yeelde theyr Citie? yet how eaſily did God deſtroy and ſcatter ſuche a Captayne, ſuche an Armie, ſo many engins of warre by the hand of a woman? What ſhall we ſay of ſo many kings as were linked togither agaynſte <hi>Ioſua,</hi> and ſo many nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſte the onely <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the time of <hi>Gideon</hi> and others? Who woulde not haue perſwaded him ſelfe of his good ſucceſſe? And who woulde not haue exhorted the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> to yeelde them ſelues, eſpecially if they had compared armour to armour, ancients to ancients, men to men, countrey to countrey. But how fooliſh and fondly did they triumph <note place="margin">Iudi. 7. &amp; 8.</note> before the victorie? Let Princes and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ceaſſe, let them ceaſſe (I ſaye) to fire theyr hartes in Caſtels, Fortes, Captaynes, Armies, monie, or any lyke thing, whiche worldlings haue in price and only eſteeme. Let them rather conſider the terrible threats
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6973:22"/> of God, left in this worlde, whereby men are drawen from fragile to firme things, from fleſh to ſpirit, from ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to God. God ſpeaketh by the mouth of Eſay: Wo vnto them that <note place="margin">Eſa. 50. &amp; 31.</note> goe downe into <hi>Egipt</hi> for help and ſtay vpon horſes, and truſt in charets, bycauſe they are many, and in horſemen bycauſe they are very ſtrong: but they looke not to the holy one of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> nor ſeeke vnto the Lorde: for when the Lorde ſhall ſtretche out hys hande, the helper ſhall fall, and they ſhall altogyther fayle. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpeaketh in lyke manner. The Kyng <note place="margin">Pſal. 33.</note> is not ſaued by the multitude of an hoſt, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the mighty man deliuered by greate ſtrength.</p>
            <p>A horſe is a vayne help and ſhall not dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner any by hys great ſtrength. Beholde, the eye of the Lorde is vppon them that feare him and truſt in his mercie, to deliuer theyr ſoules from death, and to preſerue them in famine. In theſe wordes, the ſpirite of GOD comprehendeth all ſuche t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings, as menne make accompt of to atchieue waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie affayres: yet they ſo paynte them out with ſignificante tearmes, that if all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly might were knitte togither, you maye not aſcribe victory vnto them for that
<pb facs="tcp:6973:23"/> they ſhall vaniſh away like ſmoke, and bee ſcartered like chaffe before the face of the wind in the day of battell.</p>
            <q>It is the Lord alone then at whoſe hande wee muſt aske counſayle. It is the Lorde that when man determineth proſperitie, in pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling backe his hand ſendeth aduerſitie. And agayne, it is he alone, that when men haue <note place="margin">Pſal. 30. Pſal. 107.</note> heauineſſe in the euening, ſendeth ioy in the morning, and deliuereth them out of al diſtreſſe.</q>
            <p>I Woulde not haue any to gather hereof, <note place="margin">How farre policie and humane po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is to be folowed.</note> that I reiect the foreſight and prudent policie of the Magiſtrates: for no man (but he that is ſtarke madde) wold haue them ſo wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, that as the ſuperſtitious Iewes woulde not take armour vpon them for their neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie defence on the Sabboth day, ſo that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhoulde caſt away lawfull meanes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them ſelues. But I vrge this to my port habilitie, that they firſt ſeeke help at Gods had, and then mans lawfull ayde, which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue on euery ſide well furniſhed themſelues withall, euen then I exhorte them alſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend totally vppon God. And I woulde not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6973:23"/> haue them dull or ſlouthfull: for albeit God do without intermiſſion care and labour for <note place="margin">Preparation for warre neceſſarie.</note> them: yet they ought to be workers withall (if I may ſo ſpeake) and folow him ſhewing them the way: and if any want by humane imperfection, I woulde haue them to ſolace them ſelues in the perfection of God. For as in maladies and ſickneſſe of our bodies, we go vnto the Phiſition to recouer health: Euen ſo it is fitte and conuenient in ſome times and ſeaſons to haue in readineſſe munimentes of warre to withſtand our enimies. God is not pleaſed with carrleſneſſe: he is tempted and diſpleaſed with negligence in all conditions and callings. The conflict of Chriſt with the <note place="margin">Math. 4.</note> Deuill in the wilderneſſe teacheth vs not to be idle. And the wiſe man <hi>Syrach</hi> ſayeth, He
<note place="margin">Syrach.</note> that loueth daunger ſhall periſh therin. They muſt therefore bend all their force to ſaue and preſerue their charge. They ought to approoue all good meanes and vſe all honeſt conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to ordeyne profitable and commodious things for the common wealth. But this caution ought alwayes to be obſerued: that they doe not make the Lady the handmayde, and the handmayde the Lady, but that they make the Lorde their ſhootanker: that they ſo
<pb facs="tcp:6973:24"/> procide artillarie and engins of warre, that the Lorde may be the moderatour and direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the ſame, otherwiſe without God, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons will wooke their owne woundes, and ſtrength will be their confuſion. Proude <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14. Pharao.</note> folowed the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> with ſo mighty an Army, that the hearts of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> melted with feare, but God was againſte him, who ſtroke his ſhoulders with a ſuddayne terrour; and vnpinned the Charret wheeles, and tooke them away with ſo mighty and miraculous a bande, that the <hi>Egiptians</hi> cried, we will flie, we will flie, for the Lord fighteth for Iſraell. <note place="margin">Eugenius. Arbogaſtus.</note> When the two Tyrauntes <hi>Eugenius</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bogaſtus</hi> endeauoured after the example of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus</hi> the Apoſtata, to reduce the ſuperſtition <note place="margin">Munition without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> of the Gentiles into Europe, and were furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with many thouſandes of bloudy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nims, that <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperiour hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was ſtrike<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with fear and herror at their vie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, be himſelf ſpent al the night in prayer, and receyued comforte in a viſion of good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent. The day folowing, the battayle was <note place="margin">Theodoſius.</note> ioyned, in the firſt charge, many of <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> ſouldiers were put to flight, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour being in a great agonie of mind, falleth <note place="margin">A miracle.</note> flat vpon the ground, he ſigheth and groneth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6973:24"/> in his ſoule, he perceth the heauens with pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, he is heard of God, who raiſing a mighty ſtrong wind, blowing toward the face of the <note place="margin">So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rates lib. 5. cap. 24.</note> Tirants, which violently turned backe againe the arrowes and dartes ſent from the infidels hoſt into their owne harts and bowels. And finally, God with his elementes fighting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, put them to moſt horrible ſham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and confuſion. For <hi>Eugenius</hi> falling vppon his knees before the Emperoure to obtayne mercie, had his head cut off by <hi>Theodoſius</hi> Souldiours, beyng in ſome rage, and <hi>Arbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſtus</hi> the author of that calamirie and bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, after he had fledde two dayes and ſawe no hope of life, he fell (lyke vnto <hi>Saul)</hi> vppon his ſword, and powred out his bloud. Of this miraculous victory writeth the Poet <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianus.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>O nimium dilecte deo, cui militat aether,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi> Et coniurati veniunt ad claſsica venti.</hi>
               </l> 
            </q>
            <p>Whoſoeuer therefore can ſay truly of them ſelues, Some truſt in Chariols, and ſome in Hories, but wee will remember the name of the Lord: may be bold to ſay that whiche fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pſalm: They are brought down and fallen, but we are riſen and ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpright.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6973:25"/>
            <p>But that the difference betwene dinine and <note place="margin">A difference betweene humane and diuine help.</note> humane help may be more lueulent, I thought it conuenient to adioyne the ſpeeche of Dauid vttered at what time he marched againſt mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous <hi>Goliath</hi> the Philiſtine. For out of the wordes of that moſt renoumed captaine and champion, this diuerſitie will appeare. Thou <note place="margin">Pſal. 17.</note> (ſayth Dauid) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meſt vnto me with a ſword, and with a ſpeare, and with a ſhielde: but I come to thee in the name of the Lord of hoſts, the God of the hoſte of Iſraell, whome thou rayleſt vpon. This day ſhall the Lorde cloſe thee in my hande, and I ſhall ſmite thee, and take thy head from thee, and I will giue the carkaſes of the hoſt of the Philiſtines this day vnto the foules of the heauens, and to the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of the earth, that all the world may know that Iſraell had a God: and that all this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie may know, that the Lorde ſaueth not with ſword nor with ſpeare, for the battayle is the Lordes, and he will giue you into oure handes. Suche was the voyce and hearte of Dauid, wherin his inuincible faith is euident to haue done more wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derful things tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either his enimies or his own cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reymen wer able to doe wyth policie or armoure. Surely this notable courage in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liuing Lord
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6973:25"/> might happely ſeeme in the eyes of carnall men, to be raſhneſſe and not boldneſſe, fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and not wiſdome, that a dwarffe would fight with a Gyant, a boye with a man of flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing age, vnarmed againſt one wel armed, ignorant of war againſt an old beaten ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, a ſherphook &amp; a ſling, againſt a ſpear, ſword and ſhield. Ind yet the victorie fell to this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely ſide: ſuche an approued cote armour is Gods name, which all men ought to accompt their chiefe poſte and piller, their hauen &amp; ſure anker. <hi>Achior</hi> Captayne of the ſonnes of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inon,</hi> in that his notable oration before <hi>Holo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iudeth. 5. and. 6.</note> confirmeth, that the Iewes whileſt they ſinned not before their God, proſpered againſt their puiſant enimyes euery where, not with bowe, ſwoord or ſhielde: for it was the Lord that with his miracles and wonders fought for them, and gaue them victorie in the day of battayle. Therefore to conclude this place, you playnly ſee that Princes &amp; Magiſtrates ought not only to be buſied in prouyding humayne helpe, but their principall care ought to bee in ſeruing the Lord, in obeying his worde, and fearing his holy name: ſo may they ſafely ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and grounde themſelues vppon gods moſt comfortable promiſes, which he can and will
<pb facs="tcp:6973:26"/> performe, bothe bicauſe hee is able, and moſte <note place="margin">Pſal. 145.</note> of all power and might: and alſo is louing and mercifull, and will fulfill the deſires of them that feare him and call vppon him faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The thirde Conſolation is in the great loue and fauour of God toward the Magiſtrate, commaunding his people moſt ſeuerely to reuerence and obey them.</head>
               <p>As by a ſecrete inſpiration and inwarde motion of nature we are taught to loue and reuerence our parentes: euen ſo by the ſame wee are induced to obey and honour the Magiſtrates. And as God doth reuenge with moſt ſharpe puniſhementes the wilfull ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borneneſſe of the one, ſo doth he neuer holde giltleſſe the diſobedience of the other: end ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee giueth a ſerious and ſeuere precept, by <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> his electe and choſen veſſell Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that men ſhould giue to the higher powers, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, feare, and honour, calling them by the name of his officers or miniſters: by whoſe hande as he doeth puniſhe the wicked, ſo doth he cheriſh and defende the good and innocent.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6973:26"/> Which title giuen by God, maketh them <note place="margin">Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Gods in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture.</note> more noble and renouned than their robes and ornaments of ſilkes, purple, ſiluer, gold or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſtones: yea if you put together all dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the earth, all theſe will not ſo auaunce a Magiſtrate, as one ſhorte title giuen him
<note place="margin">Pſal. 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> by God. <hi>Dauid</hi> vſeth a lyke ſtill, ſaying: God ſtandeth in the aſſembly of Gods, bee iudgeth amongeſt Gods. Heere the heauenly Prophet calleth them Gods, which name ſo high and full of maitſtie they haue, by reaſon of their office and miniſterye which they execute in Gods roome heere in earth, in doing of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and iuſtice, in puniſhing ſinne and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, in comforting the widdowes and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe, in deſending the vertuous and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent. <note place="margin">Exo. 20.</note> And in another place: Thou ſhalt not rayle vppon the Goddes, neyther ſpeake e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill of the rulers of the people.</p>
               <p>Heere Sainte <hi>Hierome</hi> tranſlateth <hi>Elohim Dijs,</hi> in engliſhe Gods, bicauſe of the workes annexed (as is aforeſayde) exeeuteth to their office and callyng. Nowe to omitte in Gods lighte howe pretious and deare the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats <note place="margin">The ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the magiſtrat.</note> are: let vs weigh the ineuitable neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, and vnſpeakable commoditie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er powers bring to mortal me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which we may
<pb facs="tcp:6973:27"/> gather from gods mouth, who threatning vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Iewes ſubuerſion and deſtruction of themſelues and their Citie, ſpeaketh in thys wiſe. <hi>The Lord of hoſtes will take away from</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſai. cap. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieruſalem &amp; from Iuda the ſtay &amp; ſtrength, euen all the ſtay of bread, and all the ſtay of water.</hi> The ſtrong man and the man of war, the Iudge and the Prophete, the prudent and the aged: The Captayne of fiftie and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, and the counſeller, and the cunning artificer, and the eloquent man. And I will appoynt children to be their Princes, &amp; babes ſhall rule ouer them. You ſee that when good <note place="margin">The miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſtate of countres in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates.</note> rulers and counſellers doe wante in common wealthes, in ſteede of ioye there ariſeth ſorow, in ſteede of charitie diſcorde, in ſtead of peace warre, in ſteade of proſperitie, all miſerie and calamitie. For, to take away the Magiſtrate, is euen as you would take the expert ſhipma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter out of the ſhip, or as you would ſet wylde horſes to drawe a Charet without a guyde. Whereof the one runneth headelong vppon rockes and quickſandes: the other ouerturneth all, not without extreme perill and daunger to themſelues. For in ſuch ſeaſons and tempeſt the wordes of the ſame Prophet are alwayes <note place="margin">Eſai. 3.</note> verified. The people ſhalbe oppreſſed one of an
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6973:27"/> other, and euery one by his neighbour: the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhal preſume againſt the auntient, and the vyle againſt the honorable: when euery one ſhal take hold of his brother of the houſe of his father &amp;c. And for that without Magiſtrates, no ſocietie and felowſhip can ſtand amongeſt men, ſeeing by the infection of the deuill, all are readie and inclined to offer iniuries and wronges, and to commit deteſtable and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable actes, the will of almightie God is, that we ſhould not only honour them, but alſo moſt earneſtly pray for their long &amp; hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance, by whoſe meane we are ſhiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from woe and miſery: Who (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> writeth) doe partly diſtribute gods gifts, and partly conſerue them amongeſt men ſtanding alwayes as King <hi>Alfonſus</hi> was wont to ſay
<note place="margin">Alfonſus.</note> in defence of the lawe and people, watching alwaye for the peace and ſafetie of the ſame. Hereof wee haue preſident in the worthie let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Hieremie</hi> the Prophet, ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the Iewes <note place="margin">Hiere. 29.</note> who were led captiues for their ſinnes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities from <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> into <hi>Babilon</hi> by the hand of <hi>Nabuchodonozer.</hi> Seeke (ſaith God) the proſperitie of the Citie, whether I haue cauſed you to be caryed away captyues, and pray vnto the Lord for it, for in the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb facs="tcp:6973:28"/> you ſhall haue peace. Sainte <hi>Paul</hi> in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <note place="margin">Prayer for the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> giueth lyke precept to his people and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, ſaying: I exhort therefore, that firſt of all ſupplications, prayers, interceſſions, and giuing of thankes bee made for all men: for Kings and for all that bee in aucthoritie, that wee maye leade a quyet and a peaceable way of life, in all godlineſſe and honeſtie: For this is good and acceptable in the ſight of God our ſauiour. Theſe and ſuch lyke places may woorthely and in deede comfort and ſtaye the mynde of Princes: for they doe argue and giue a firme and an infallible document, the liuing Lorde to haue a ſingular prouidence ouer rulers and gouernours. <hi>Tertullian</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth <note place="margin">Tertulia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus apolo. cap. 30.</note> how earneſtly the Primatiue Church prayed for their Princes in theſe words: Wee Chriſtians caſt vp our eyes to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, our ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds ſpred abroad, bicauſe they are cleane: our heads vncouered, bicauſe we are not aſhamed: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any monitor, bicauſe wee praye from the bottom of our beartes, and doe make interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vnto God for all Emperours, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it would pleaſe his maieſtie to giue vnto them long life, ſure palace, truſtie honeſt ſubiectes, quiet regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in fine, all good things that maye come to man. There is extante a paterne and example of perfite prayer for Princes, indy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6973:28"/> by the holy ghoſt, and penned by his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ſecretarie <hi>Dauid</hi> throughout the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <note place="margin">Pſal. 20.</note> Pſalme, with an aſſured promiſe that God will heare ſuch praiers: which Pſalme I wiſh all noble men to make familiar vnto them.</p>
               <p>Now albeit in theſe words of God alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die produced, ſufficient might ſeeme to bee vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered <note place="margin">Euill thoughtes againſt the magiſtrats forbidden.</note> for the ancthoritie and conſolation of Princes: yet the almightie Lorde not ſatiſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therewithall, proceedeth in reſtreyning ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects in ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derous ſpeeches &amp; curſed thoughtes againſt their Magiſtrates.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalte not rayle vppon the Iudges, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Exo 22.</note> 
                  <hi>ſpeake euill of the ruler of the people.</hi> Which precept <hi>Salomon</hi> the wyſeſt that euer was or ſhal bee, expoundeth at large in thys wyſe. <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Reg. 5. Eccleſi. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>thought,</hi> neither curſe the rich in thy bedcham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: for the birds of heauen ſhal carie thy voice, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which hath wings ſhall declare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter. Men for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part think their loyaltie well diſcharged if they ſhew not diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally: neither doe they accompt it any offence if their hartes boyle with rancor and malice. But <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter is far otherwiſe, ſhewing true and faithful obedience to conſiſt not only in the hand, but alſo in the harte: wee haue a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſaying (thought is free) but that
<pb facs="tcp:6973:29"/> hath force before men only. For as mens ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes are ſo dull that they can not ſmell ſuch things incloſed ſo deepely in the moſte hid places of man: yet the breath and vnſautrye ſmell of them perecth the cloudes and aſcendeth vp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the maieſtie of God, for ſo muche are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in <hi>Salomons</hi> words, <hi>That which hath wings ſhall declare the matter.</hi> The ſentence of <note place="margin">Ibicus.</note> 
                  <hi>Ibycus</hi> approueth this ſentence. When <hi>Ibycus</hi> fell into the handes of theeues, and perceiued that they would eruelly murder him, and ſaw no man preſent to reſkewe him: he happened to ſee a company of Cranes flying ouer their heads, who caſting vp his eyes and ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds moſt lamentably and earneſtly, prayed them not to ſuffer his death vnreuenged. The the eues ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly laughed at that his playnte, thinking it vmpoſſible that euer the Crames ſhould bring to light that haynous facte and offence. But not long after, it happened two of theſe mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers to ſitte on a benche in the Citie, when Cranes flying with a noyſe that way, one of them ſayde to his felowe ſkoffingly, <hi>Beholde the reuengers of Ibycus:</hi> which wordes one or two ſitting by (who hartely loued the man for his ſingular learning &amp; vertue) ouerharde, and conceyuing ſome ſuſpition, cauſed theſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6973:29"/> two felowes to be apprehended and impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and laſtly with tormentes to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: whereby the cruell murder was diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and they according to good <hi>Ibycus</hi> prayer condemned and executed. Heere <hi>Salomons</hi> wordes had their working. <hi>That which hath wings ſhall declare the matter.</hi> The wiſe king did well vnderſtand, and wee doe feele by our ſelues, that Nature being our parent, or rather our ſtepdame, hath poured into mankynd ſuch filthy froth and drouſie dregges, that wee doe not only iudge ſiniſterlie of others: but are te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly &amp; malitiouſly bent to our ſuperiours: and out of thoſe the ſinckes and puddelles, the raging floudes of murmuring and blaſphee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, of ſedition and rebellion, doe guſhe and breake. <hi>Salomon</hi> therefore ſheweth the duties of honeſt and faithfull ſubiectes, namely, that as often as they ſee any ſeditious <hi>Abſolon,</hi> or ſkornefull <hi>Caine,</hi> or rayling <hi>Semei,</hi> that then they ſhould be as it were deaffe, dumbe and blinde, that they ſhould brydle their carnal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, that they ſhould giue no credite to rumours and tales, that they ſhould not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue any euill of Princes and rulers: but if they happely heare or ſee any ſpottes in them, to couer them with the cloke of ignorance and
<pb facs="tcp:6973:30"/> patience.</p>
               <p>It conſequently foloweth of the premiſes, that whether it be <hi>Nabuchodonozer, Zedechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> or <hi>Ezechias,</hi> that doe rule and gouerne, and to what exigent ſo euer the people are brought in ciuill cauſes, they maye not by anyt meanes practiſe ſleights, deceites, ſeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt their prince: al wayes are rather to be attempted, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe venemous ointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; plaiſters, which y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vulgare ſort haue in redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; wherwith they are delited. And ſurely <note place="margin">The deuil is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</note> ſuch raſhe &amp; raging counſel, ſuch firebrands of ſedition and rebellion, proceede not of any he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roical ſpirit &amp; courage, but are kindled &amp; ſet on fyre by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furor of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deuil, vtterly to burne and conſume townes, Cities &amp; kingdomes, as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zomenus</hi> doth by a very ſtrange hiſtorie not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <note place="margin">Sozome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. lib. 7. cap. 23.</note> declare. When the Citizens of <hi>Anteoche</hi> were moued to rebell againſt <hi>Theodoſius</hi> for a greeuous tribute or ſubſidie laid vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, and were yet doubtful in mynd what to doe, the night before the vprore, a wicked fende or ſpirite appeared vnto them in the ayre in ſhape of a woman, of a houge and monſtrous ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, running hither and thither with meruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous celeritie, ſtyring the ayre, and rayſing the wynd with a great fanne, and making ſuch a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6973:30"/> noyſe as the keepers of wilde beaſts doe, when they practiſe them to fierceneſſe and crueltie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their time of bayting: with this ſtrange apparition, the deuill no doubt added furious holdneſſe or rather madneſſe to their myndes to goe forwarde in that their deteſtable enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, wherhy they had drawen vtter diſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vppon their own heades, if <hi>Elauianus</hi> their biſhop had not with his moſt humble interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion mitigated the wrathful mynd of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour. If you peruſe the hiſtories &amp; Croni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of all tymes, it will playnly appeare, that <note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians haue obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the vu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie end of rebelles. The end of thoſe that mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered <hi>Iuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Caeſar. Appianus.</hi>
                  </note> whoſoeuer reſiſted the ſupreme magiſtrat, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed vnto themſelues gods wrath and whot anger, and came to vtter ſhame and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion. Prophane writers haue obſerued, that of thoſe xx: ii. Senators, which gaue vnto <hi>Iulrus Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> in the Senate houſe xxiij. woundes, &amp; dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped his handes in bloud, not one of them liued aboue three yeeres after <hi>Caeſars</hi> death, not one of them dyed naturally in his bed, &amp; which is moſt notable, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many of them murdered them ſelues with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame weapons that perced <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars</hi> ſides. <hi>Caſsius</hi> the firſt author of this mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<note place="margin">Caſsius.</note> being by profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an epicure &amp; a ſkoffer of all talks touching heauen, hel, &amp; the immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the ſoule: as he was fighting obſtinatly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> battail at <hi>Philippos</hi> againſt <hi>Octauianus</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6973:31"/> and <hi>Anthonius,</hi> ſawe a ſouldier exceding the common ſtature of man, comming agaynſt him with maine vppon a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olie courſer, hauing a terrible looke, armed with purple or binddie harneſſe, and fiercely charging his ſtaffe vppon him, wherewithall <hi>Caſsius</hi> being amazed, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth his backe and runneth away: But the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit folowing, cryeth aloude vnto him: <hi>VVhat</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Valer. max. lib. 1. cap. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>more remayneth for thee to doe, if thou think this murder nothing?</hi> Thou haſte not ſlayne <hi>Caeſar</hi> O <hi>Caſsius:</hi> for no heauenly power can be murdered: but in that thou haſt vſed viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce agaynſt his earthly bodie, thou haſte deſerued Gods wrath againſt thee. So <hi>Caſsius</hi> falling vppon his owne weapon through diſpayre, at the laſt learned the rewarde of rebellion, and that there is a God in heauen, a ſoule in man,
<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> a deuill in hell. <hi>M. Brutus</hi> alſo, the chiefeſt in credite with the people of all that companye, and one who had receiued greate benefites of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> whom he loued ſo dearely, that euen at his laſt gaſps he called vnto him and ſaid my ſonne <hi>Brutus</hi> ſawe at the battayle aforeſayde a mightie big blacke <hi>Iudian</hi> fighting agaynſt him, and wounding his ſoldiers on euery ſidr, which (as <hi>Valerius</hi> writeth) was euen god him <note place="margin">Valerius Max. ca. 5.</note> ſelfe that caſt dartes at him, and fought againſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6973:31"/> him. <hi>Brutus</hi> being a <hi>Stoicke</hi> and an imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator of his vncle <hi>Cato,</hi> ſeeing both God and man fight againſt him, conueighed him ſelfe out of the battayle, and when <hi>Strato</hi> the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toritian being often and earneſtly deſired to thruſt his ſword in him, would not in ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie a caſe gratifie him, he himſelf perſed his hart with his own dagger. The poets in their fables of the ſlaughter of Gyantes by <hi>Iupiter</hi> and of the <hi>Phlegians</hi> in <hi>Theſsalia,</hi> being ſuche
<note place="margin">The <hi>Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gians.</hi>
                  </note> as were ſeditious, and forced neither for God nor man, and therefore were caryed quick into hell with a flud raiſed by <hi>Neptune,</hi> doe admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh men of the vnhappy end of rebelles and Traytours, of whom <hi>Virgill</hi> writeth.</p>
               <q>
                  <note place="margin">Virg. Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neid. lib. 6.</note>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Phlegyaſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> miſerrimus omnes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi> Admonet, &amp; magna teſtatur voce per vmbras</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l> 
                     <hi>Diſcite iuſtitiam moniti, &amp; non temnere diuos.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Of the laſte verſe there is a very memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note place="margin">Sabellicus.</note> narration, which bicauſe it is not onlye pleaſant but profitable, I thought it not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meete for this place. There goeth a greth a great talk in <hi>Italie,</hi> of a woman who being brought vp in ſpinning and carding, or otherwiſe berye ſimply, was as ſoone as ſhee came to womans
<pb facs="tcp:6973:32"/> ſtate, rapte (as it were) and inſpired not onlye with a ſpirit of propheſie, but indued with ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, in ſuch ſorte that ſhee was had in greate admiration of all men. <hi>Lazarus Bonami</hi> an Italian, a man of greate name for his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, was moued with the great fame to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit hir, and to approue the trueth of the ſame: for it was giuen out of hir, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe wold (as ſhe was caryed with inward motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) intreat and diſcourſe of, humayne and deuyne learnyng profoundly, and abſolue and anſwere vnto the moſt difficulte and barde queſtions. At bys <note place="margin">The moſt excellent berſe in <hi>Vergil.</hi>
                  </note> comming he demmau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth hir which was the beſt verſe in all <hi>Vergil</hi> his work: ſhe anſwered, </p>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Diſcite iustitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moniti, &amp; non temnere diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <p>And further added with ſome behemencie, <hi>Thou arte anſwered, Bonami,</hi> Departe &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me no more. And aſſuredly ſhee was not deceyued, for if you turne all Prophane Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets in Greeke or Latine, no one verſe may be in any reſpect hereunto compared.</p>
               <p>But to my purpoſe, I am of thys opinyon, that in moſte lamentable caſes of ſubiectes, euen in meere ſeruitude men ought to vſe all modeſtie and humilitie toward their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, leaſt by malaparte and obſtinate dealing, they rather exaſperate and incenſe them, than
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6973:32"/> pacifye and coole them. Fierce Lyons beyng dalyed withall, cheriſhed and gentlye ſtroked, <note place="margin">In what ſorte it is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient for ſubiects to deale with ſcuere magiſtrats.</note> doe laye aſyde after a ſorte their ſauage cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and beyng pleaſantly wraſtled with, will ſhewe themſelues weake: but if a man ſhew roughneſſe and ſharpeneſſe, and vſe vyolence and force, he ſhall wiſhe himſelfe without the compaſſe of their claſpes. So is it with prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Magiſtrates, who in ſome reſpectes are of lyke nature and inclination with Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: whoſe heades (as I ſayd) may be ſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked but ſoftly &amp; ſmothlye, but if a man wring and pricke them, or otherwiſe offend them, he is but caſt away. And if ther happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ariſe ſome intollerable Tyrant, or if a good and vertuous Prince doe degenerate into wickedneſſe and doe oppreſſe his people, yet ſuche burdens art ſeldome eaſed with ſuche leuers. But it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth for the moſt parte, that the grudgyng people whom <hi>Salomon</hi> chaſtized with roddes, <note place="margin">1. Reg. 12.</note> and loded with light burdens: <hi>Reboam</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected with ſcourges, and ouercharged with heauy lodes. As the Poets deuiſe of the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Hidra,</hi> whoſe head when <hi>Hercules</hi> cut off, he ſaw two ariſe out of band in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place: the Prince therefore and Magiſtrate, howe ſocuer hee bee inclyned, hee is Gods gyfte:
<pb facs="tcp:6973:33"/> but he is a moſt heauenly treaſure if be execute his calling with equitie &amp; iuſtice: vnto whom ſuch men as ſhewe diſobedience, are termed in ſcripture the ſonnes of <hi>Beliall.</hi> And this is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly <note place="margin">1. Reg. 20.</note> true, that if at any tyme the prince appeare ouer weake for rebelles, if he bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned and at laſt vanquiſhed, then the Lord himſelf deſcendeth into the field, to reuenge the contumelie and iniurie done to his officer, as in the Chapiter folowing ſhall more aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly appeare. Wherefore it apperteyneth to ſubiectes, not only for conſcience ſake, and to auoyd damnation, but alſo for worldly peace and quietneſſe, euen in the ſeuere and ſharpe regyment of their Princes, to referre them and their cauſe to almightie God, who onlie is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by his ineſtimable power eyther to alter their myndes and actions for the ſubiects com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte, or vtterly to take them awaye for their quietneſſe.</p>
               <p>Hereof wee haue many examples ſeruyng <note place="margin">Gods wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuering his people from Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans.</note> for the inſtruction and admonition of ſuche as be placed in high dignitie, but eſpecially for the ſolare and comfort of ſeelie ſubiectes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weried with the burthenous yoke of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſſe Magiſtrates, where in the wonderfull iudgement and counſayle of God doth in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6973:33"/> more manifeſtly ſhewe themſelues. We reade of ſuch as were euen now aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the higheſt dignitie, and adorned with all glory and honor: by and by to be throwen downe ſuddenly by incredible meanes, and al their power and ſtrength to haue bin layde in the duſt. Who can denit, but that Gods dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with <hi>Nabuchodonozer</hi> the Lorde of the whole earthe, farre exceedeth mans capacitie? who for his intollerable pride, ſuſteined a new puniſhment, lying out amongſt brute beaſts, and wandring with them vntill ſeauen yeeres were come and gone. Moreouer we reade <note place="margin">The ſtrange and variable eſtate of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires.</note> partly in Scripture, partly in other credible monumentes, that by Gods diſpenſations, proude <hi>Tyre</hi> to haue bin proſtrate and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen by the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> the <hi>Egyptians</hi> to haue bin ouerthrowen by the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> to haue bin ſpoyled by the <hi>Chalde is</hi> and <hi>Babilonians,</hi> the <hi>Babilonians</hi> to haue bin vanquiſhed by the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> the <hi>Perſians</hi> by the <hi>Greekes,</hi> the power of the <hi>Greekes</hi> agayne to haue bin conquered by the <hi>Romanes:</hi> and we ſee laſtly the maieſtie of the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire dayly weakened, by that cruell enimie of Chriſtendome the <hi>Turke,</hi> who in taking our Caſtles and Cities, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compteth
<pb facs="tcp:6973:34"/> it but a ſporte to wade in the bloud of his owne Souldiers, ſo that hee may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne hys deſire. It were a long proceſſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly to proſecute all cauſes of ſuche mutations and chaunges in Empires and Kingdomes: but this ſhall be ſufficient for my purpoſe, to notifie out of the holy Scripture, by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the Kings of <hi>Iuda</hi> and <hi>Iſraell,</hi> who <note place="margin">The cauſe why king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes are puniſhed.</note> albeit they were by Gods election appointed to rule his choſen people, &amp; had receyued more excellent benefites at Gods hand, than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Gentiles: yet if at any time they ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed themſelues vnthankfull, if they became ſtubborne and declined from Godlineſſe, they felt by &amp; by the ſword, either of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Babilonians,</hi> or of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> or of ſome other enimie, and ſometime were led into moſt lamentable cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie and bondage. Therefore it is the Lord, that at his owne pleaſure, without any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of mortall men, doth alter and tranſpoſe kings &amp; kingdoms. It is God that exalteth &amp; <note place="margin">Dauid.</note> bringeth lowe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bleſſeth and beateth Princes &amp; Magiſtrates, in ſuche times and places as it ſeemeth beſt to his maieſtie, ſo that the ſubiects neede not to deuiſe and buſie themſelues with violence, to reforme or depoſe their gonernors. <note place="margin">Syrach. 10.</note> And ſeeing that (as the wiſe man ſayth) The
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6973:34"/> gouernour of the earthe, is in the hande of the Lord, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time is, he ſhall ſet vp a proſitable ruler ouer it: It is the part of ſubiectes, thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and dutifully to reuerence ſuche, whome God hath appoynted to ſupply his own place in Earth. And ſurely, our owne quietnes may perſwade vs, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> conſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all eſtates may requite vs, and Chriſtian religion will ſtraitly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund vs ſo to do, namely, to reſtrayne out thoughts, tongs, &amp; hands, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doing any thing againſt thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be placed in authority ouer vs.</p>
               <p>But here riſeth queſtion of the boundes <note place="margin">Of the limits of obedience.</note> of obedience, whether ſubiects ought to obey their magiſtrates, if they commaunde things contrary to the law of God and the lawe of nature. Vnto the whiche queſtion, we ſhall anſwere both ſoundly and ſafely, if we exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what honor is, and gather a definition <note place="margin">what obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is.</note> or declaration hereof out o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods word. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor hath ſundry ſlgnifications in the ſcripture, but as it ſerueth to this cauſe, To honor, is to feare, to loue, to reuerence, to obey, To obey (I ſay) as it were vnto God, who exacteth the ſame at our hands, and vnto whom we know out obedience acceptable: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magiſtrate ſhal eyther do or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund any wicked thing, wee may not obey, eyther by imitation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or
<pb facs="tcp:6973:35"/> by action: For the latter commaundementes haue relation vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt. But we are taught in the ſecond commaundement, the ſinnes and iniquities of the fathers to be puniſhed in the children vnto thr third and fourth generation: Therefore they are not to be obeyed in thyngs againſt God and nature. <hi>Ionathas</hi> hearkened not vnto his father <hi>Saule,</hi> when he ſought the life of <hi>Dauid:</hi> and is therefore greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in the word of God. The three com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of <hi>Daniell</hi> obeyed <hi>Nabuchodonozer</hi> in politicall things, they loued him, and they reuerenced him as a mightie Monarch and moſt bountifull prince: but when he exected I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie, they neglected his power and might. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> the commaunder of obedience <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> due to fathers and Magiſtrates, when the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niors of the people woulde haue ſtopped hys mouth from preaching of the Lorde Ieſus, he aunſwered earneſily, <hi>VVe ought rather to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Act. 4. &amp; 5.</note> 
                  <hi>obey God than men.</hi> But what neede I to ſeeke many proofes, ſeeing the Lorde him ſelfe hath comprehended all ſuch authorities in one ſentence? If any man come to me and hate not his father and mother, and wife, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and brethren, and ſiſters, yea and his own life <note place="margin">Math. 10. li. 14</note> life alſo, he cannot be my diſciple. It is out of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6973:35"/> all doubt, that the magiſtrates ought not to commaund any thing againſte God and the lawe of nature, and they ſhould bend all theyr ſtudie ſo to gouerne, that their ſubiects may feele and taſt, that they haue their authoritie from God, and that they vſe the ſame in God. But if they enterpriſe any thing without that compaſſe, the ſubiect ſhoulde prepoſterouſly prefer the ſeruant before the maſter.</p>
               <p>It may be demaunded, what if the Prince <note place="margin">A queſtion. What ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects may do whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are oppreſſed.</note> ſeeing his will and commaundement negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, vſe extreame executions againſt ſuch as will not obey him, may the ſubiect reſiſt with violence? I ſay no, no violence by no meanes. Let him diſobey, not in rebelling, but in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering all iniuries and oppreſſions. Let hym <note place="margin">Subiectes may not infer but ſuſtayne iniuries.</note> not by any calamitie be ſtirred to lift vp hys hand againſt a Ruler, and ſo offend the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of God. And if he cannot by way of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition and ſupplication mitigate the Princes anger: neyther yet by flight and departure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde the ſame: it remayneth that he commit him ſelfe and his cauſe to that iuſt iudge, who hath reſerued vengeance to him ſelfe, and hath promiſed to powre it vpon wicked and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <note place="margin">Deu. 32. Rom. 12.</note> perſons, at ſuch a time as al their limmes and ſtayes ſhall ſlide from them. The violence
<pb facs="tcp:6973:36"/> and extreame crueltie whiche wicked rulers do vnto Chriſtian ſubiects, are of two ſortes: For ſome touch temporall things only as our bodies, our lands, our liuings: others do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly things as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of gods word, faith in Chriſt Ieſus, &amp; the true worſhipping of God, &amp; ſuch like. Now as for our Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things, a Chriſtian may ſuſtayne damage &amp; vtter loſſe of al his goodes, yea, and of his life alſo, &amp; yet may keepe his faith and hope of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, firme &amp; ſtable. But he may not ſuffer thoſe diuine &amp; heauenly things to be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. For there is no creature, bee he neuer ſo mighty, that is able to ſpoile me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. Beſides that, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> taking away of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> things lie not in the power of the magiſtrate, but remayne by Gods grace, in the will and conſent of the beleener. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauenly Lord onely, is of power to exerciſe iudgemente in ſemblable caſes, eyther to reiect men and caſt them away according to his iuſtice, or to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them according to his mercie to eternall life. So that albeit the Prince woulde with a thouſande torments driue vs to imbrace ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and idolatrie, we are neyther bound to obey him, neyther yet is he able (if God bee on our ſide) to vanquiſh and conquere vs.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:6973:36"/>
               <p>Moreouer, there is no ſmall difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <note place="margin">A great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> thoſe men that doe patiently tolerate vniuſt violence, &amp; thoſe that do offer iniurious viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to others. A Chriſtian may ſuffer with a good and quiet conſcience iniuſtice, but hee cannot in like ſort practiſe and execute vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful things. In all actions therefore, the perfit line of Gods law is to be conſidered: and that our deſire &amp; wil is to do good things, and to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. And if being deteined in bonds or impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts or otherwiſe, we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſerue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Lord our God, &amp; yet do earneſtly wiſh and deſire to do it: In ſuche caſe our willes and intentes are accepted before God for acts and deede. Againe, if the prince do command vs to do y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which is to be auoided, no man may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him ſelfe before God, by reaſon of that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement: neyther wil it be a ſufficient diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge vnto him to aunſwere, I was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, I was compelled, I did it vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly. S. Iohn ſaith, this is the victorie whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che
<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 5.</note> ouercommeth the world, euen your faithe. And howe ſhall we reſiſt Sathan the greate prince of this world, if we be ſuch weakelings that we cannot reſiſt no not the worlde? And how ſhal we reſiſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world, if through the threats &amp; torments of one worldly prince,
<pb facs="tcp:6973:37"/> we turne our backes from the truth. He that is regenerate by Gods ſpirite, may truly ſay, I do not now liue, but Chriſt liueth in me: I <note place="margin">Gala. 2. Rom. 8.</note> am perſwaded, that neyther death nor life, nor Angels nor Principalities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, &amp;c. ſhall be able to ſeparate vs from the loue of God, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lorde. There is a mirror or glaſſe of ſuch innocent and vprighte dealing in that worthy man <hi>Papinianus,</hi> in <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Papinianus</hi> the ſincere lawyer. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lius Sparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus in Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nino.</hi>
                  </note> profeſſion a ciuill lawyer, in religion an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thnike, which is as hereafter foloweth: When the Emperour <hi>Autoninus Caracalla</hi> whome ſome do cal <hi>Baſsinianus,</hi> had murthered cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vniuſtly his brother <hi>Getha</hi> in his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers lappe, who was ſo deare vnto the army, for his father <hi>Seuerus</hi> his ſake, that the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers <note place="margin">Herod. lib. 4.</note> were almoſt bent to runne vpon <hi>Baſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianus</hi> with their weapons for that fact: the Emperour dealt with <hi>Papinianus</hi> his <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeller,</hi> whom all the Souldiers reuerenced for his deepe wiſedome and vprighte Iuſtice, to defende his vnnaturall offence: vnto whome <hi>Papinianus</hi> aunſwered: Wilfull patricide (ô Emperour) is more eaſily commited than defe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d. O worthy ſentence, and well beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a counſeller and a lawyer. That good
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6973:37"/> man was more willing and readie to ſuffer like ſmart with <hi>Getha,</hi> which he knew would proceede from the Tirant for his refuſall, than to defend, or by any colour to ſmooth or cloke wilfull murder.</p>
               <p>But ſome man will ſay, if we mayntayne <note place="margin">Obiection.</note> our cauſes ſo preciſely, and withſtand the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ſo ſtubbornely, we ſhall exaſperate them, and pull the houſe vpon our owne heds. But if we yeeld vnto the time, God may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Princes heart, and we may eate our bread in reſt and quietneſſe. Vnto ſuche obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
<note place="margin">Anſwere <hi>Demades.</hi>
                  </note> I will otherwiſe aunſwere, than <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mades</hi> anſwered the <hi>Athenians</hi> in times paſt. <hi>Caſſander</hi> the Macedonian practiſed with the <hi>Athenians,</hi> that they ſhoulde worſhip Greate <hi>Alexander</hi> as a God: who ſtaggered ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what at the matter: Wherefore <hi>Caſſander</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth open warre againſte them, if they woulde not doe it. <hi>Demades</hi> made then an Oration vnto the people, and amongſt other things vſed this ſpeech: That it ſtoode them vpon ſo to conſider of heauen that they might not loſe the earthe. But I thinke it beſt to tranſpoſe the ſentence, That it ſtandeth men vpon to take heede, ſo to conſider of the earth, that they loſe not heauen. Therefore, albeit
<pb facs="tcp:6973:38"/> all potentats of the earth grinde their teeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, yet it is our parts to ſhew our bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in God. And as in worldly matters ſome vſe to ſay, <hi>Let iuſtice go forwarde, albeit all the world periſhe.</hi> So let Chriſtians ſaye, <hi>Let vs do Gods will and pleaſure, albeit hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth do periſh. Auguſtine</hi> hath a gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſaying. <hi>Men may not commit ſinne in ſhewing obedience. Daniel</hi> diſobeying the
<note place="margin">Dani. 6.</note> King, forbidding him to ſerue his God, excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him ſelfe, ſaying, <hi>Vnto thee O King, haue I done no hurt,</hi> that is to ſay, I haue not treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed againſt thee, for I haue obeyed the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God.</p>
               <p>This admonition of the limittes of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ull <note place="margin">Naturall reaſon tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to obey our ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors only, in things law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</note> obedience, is taught by perfit reaſon, and confirmed by prophane examples, acquitting s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ayes men from the ſpot of diſobedience, that bend their endeuours to obey the ſupreme power and maieſtie. <hi>Antigona</hi> grauely excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſelfe to King <hi>Creon,</hi> ſaying, that ſhe may not for his commandement or feare vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the law of nature being diuine. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Telemon</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kings ſon with vehement ſpeech defended his eſponſed wife <hi>Antigona,</hi> the <note place="margin">Apud Sopho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clem.</note> King ſaid, <hi>How dareſt thou contend with thy</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>? He anſwered, bycauſe thou wouldſt do
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:6973:38"/> monſtrous things. <hi>Creon.</hi> Do I mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrouſly to honor my eſtate, &amp; to vſe my prerogatiue? <hi>Hemon.</hi> Thou canſt not O King honor thy eſtate by any meanes, when thou diſhonoreſt God. <note place="margin">Ex Stobaeo.</note> 
                  <hi>Stobaeus</hi> reporteth a worthy anſwer gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to a yong man by one. <hi>Muſonius</hi> in thys ſort. Ther was a yong man giuen altogyther to the ſtudie of Philoſophie and other liberal ſciences, but was hindred by his father, who moſt earneſtly forbad him thoſe ſtudies, &amp; wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him to frame his life another way. Thys yong man repaireth to <hi>Muſonius,</hi> &amp; vſeth theſe words: <hi>Muſoni,</hi> are children bound to obey their pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts generally, or are ther ſome priuate cauſes excepted? vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he anſwered: In my opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is a thing very commendable for children to reuerence their parents, but it were neceſſary to know, what dutie and obedience is, and if wee conſider the contrary, namely what the vice, ſtubborneſſe and diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is; we ſhall more eaſily know the vertue. Wel then, let vs by queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſift this matter. What if a father, hauing no ſkil in Phiſick, nor kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> qualities and temperature of ſimples &amp; compounds, would command his ſon being ſick, to receiue ſome medicine, which the father thinketh profitable, but is indeed vnholeſome &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:6973:39"/> mortall: will any man accompte the ſonne diſobedient bicauſe in ſuche cauſes he bath not folowed his fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>antaſie? verily I ſuppoſe not. Moreouer if y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> father himſelf being ſicke, doe call vnto his ſon to giue him ſome meate or drinke whiche will ſatiſfie his appetite, but augment his ſickneſſe: If the ſonne giue not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate vnto his father therein, will ye pronounce him obſtinate? ſurely no man of perfect mynd will ſo iudge of him. Muche leſſe is he to bee called diſobedient, that being commanded of his father to deceyut, to ſteale, to murder, or to attempt or doe any thing vnlawfull, will not fulfil his precept and commandement. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when men refuſe to folow the willes and mindes of ſuche as do commaunde any thing vnhoneſt and vnlawful, whether they be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, fathers, or maſters, they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be fermed diſobedient, neither negligent in their dutie. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Muſonius.</hi> Touching o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gueſtions, hamely, what if the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate degenerate into Tirannie? what if he woulde bring into the countrey aliantes and ſtraung its? What if he would ſeeke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on the tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e worſhipping of God and receiue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Religion? Theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are withoute the conipaſſe of thy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:6973:39"/> my treatie (beeing a conſolation for magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates only) and cannot be diſcourſed with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny edification: neyther doe I finde any thyng written abſolutely thereof by the learned. And in deede, ſith that ſuche caſes depend vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Gods eſpeciall diſpenſation, without the whiche, nothing can bee well enterpriſed, nor more happily atchieued: it were not only pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous, but very hard to preſcribe any generall rule in ſuch caſes. Whereof that worthy <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Sarum,</hi> hauing very good occaſion to write largely by the prouocation of his aduerſarie maſter <hi>Harding,</hi> tempereth his ſtile in ſuch ſort, that albeit he ſtoppeth the Papiſts mouthes touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nobles of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: yet may the prudent reader very well <note place="margin">In the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Apologie Fol. 20. &amp;. 21</note> perceyue his vnwilling minde to wade farre in that queſtion. It is our parts that be Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen, with all gratefulneſſe of voyce and hart, to praiſe God for exempting vs out of ſuch miſerable caſes, and to pray for the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of the ſame, vnder out tender and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Lady and miſtreſſe the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, who by hir milde regime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t taketh away all occaſion of ſuche queſtions. And ſurely, ſo long as ſhe guideth the ſterne of the ſhippe, I haue good hope that we ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:6973:40"/> ſayle in the calme and peaceable ſea. But it for our ſinnes to almightie God, &amp; ſroward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towarde his maieſtie, ſhee faint or fayle, then what will be out Engliſh tune, but wo worth, and wayle away. For I ſee folowing hir dayes, the lamentable times, not of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixt <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, and <hi>Richarde</hi> the third, ſor xij. or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. yeeres, when the worlde was ſuch, as the Colyer that denied his ſeruice
<note place="margin">The daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous eſtate of this realm of England.</note> to eyther part, and profeſſed himſelfe the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels man ſcaped beſt: but the bloudy times of <hi>Ferrex</hi> and <hi>Porrex,</hi> in whome the line and of ſpring of <hi>Brute</hi> ended, after whoſe dayes this lande was rent into foure factions, and for the ſpace of 51. yeeres, there was no lawe, no iuſtice no peace, but tumults, vprorrs, ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill warres, effuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of bloud. &amp;c. The remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of theſe things, muſt needes beate a wonderfull feare and horror into our bones and bowels, and driue vs to proſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rate oure ſelues before his throne of Grace, with deepe ſighing and groning, to craue that he woulde auert and turne away thoſe ſorowfull and ruthfull dayes, or againſt thoſe times prouide for our comforts ſome <hi>Gedeon</hi> or <hi>lepthe,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe couerts we may hide our ſelurs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe terrible ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ormes and tempeſts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:6973:40"/>
               <head> 
                  <hi>The fourth Conſolation, of many examples out of diuine and prophane writers, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we ſee, that good princes &amp; magiſtrates haue bin preſerued from the furious hands of their enimies abroade and at home.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is a great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort for godly and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrates, to haue before theyr eyes the worthy examples of Kings &amp; Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the old Teſtament, and to obſerue their famous and renoumed or rather miraculous actes, which they did not by their own power and policie, but by the ayde and prouidence of God. Whereby they may both confirme and ſettle their confidence and faith in him, and alſo haue preſente admonition in all their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, by the example of others, what wayes and meanes they may vſe to auoyde perilles and dangers. <hi>Abraham</hi> the father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <note place="margin">Abraham.</note> being driuen into many greeuous miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and calamities, and toſt too and fro with great carke and care: yet for that he perſeuered firme in faith and hope, he was neuer forſaken of God, but always deliuerd out of diſtreſſe. Ind moreouer, God gaue him glory in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> day of batel. For whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Lot</hi> his brothers ſon was led <note place="margin">Gen. 14.</note> away captiue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Sodome,</hi> he broght out of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6973:41"/> that were borne and bredde in his houſe, three hundreth and eighteene perſons, and purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed diuers Kings, ſinit them, deſtroyed them, and recouered <hi>Lot</hi> his family and his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and placed him in his houſe agayne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> the Patriarche, breyng ſolde into <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ioſeph.</note> where he liued an alient and ſtraunger, and afterward was caſt into Priſon: yet tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in the liuing God, he was not only ſet at libertie, but alſo called to ſuche honor and dignitie, that vnder <hi>Pharao</hi> he was chiefe ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of the land of <hi>Egipt.</hi> Carnal reaſon would <note place="margin">Gen. 41. &amp; 42</note> thinke it vnpoſſible, that a ſeelie poore Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite, being ſold to ſtraungers, and loden with bolts of iron in priſon, ſhoulde aſpire to ſuche authoritie. But theſe are y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wonderfull works <note place="margin">Pſal. 145.</note> of God, who is nigh vnto all thoſe that call vpon him faithfully. And againe, The Lorde <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.</note> reſtoreth my ſoule, and leadeth me in the paths of righteouſneſſe for his names ſake. Yea, though I ſhould walke through the valley of the ſhadow of death, I will feare no euill, for thou art with me, thy rod, and thy ſtaffe, they comfort me. <hi>Moſes</hi> that notable Prophet, was
<note place="margin">Moſes.</note> almoſt drowned in many greeuous calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, wherein mans reaſon coulde deuiſe no helpe, nor fynde comforte, eſpecially, when bee
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6973:41"/> went before the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued with a mightie armye, hanyng before him the read Sea, and the mountaynes on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery fyde: but he both knew what God could doe, and beleued alſo that God would cauſe the Sea to ſoake into the earth, or to ſtand like a wall on both ſydes, whereby the Iſraelites might marche through on drye lande, and that the ſame ſhoulde returne agayne to bys courſe, and drowne all the <hi>Egiptians:</hi> than in any one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ote fayle in his promiſes, or relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh his elect and choſen people. Gods word can not be falſe, and therfore the Prophet ſaith, <note place="margin">Iere. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed is the man that truſteth in the Lorde, and whoſe helpe the Lord is:</hi> and in an other, place, <hi>In an acceptable time haue I heard thee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 49.</note> 
                  <hi>and in a day of ſaluation haue I helped thee, and I wil preſerue thee Ioſua</hi> ſucceding Moſes <note place="margin">Ioſua.</note> caſted many bitter cuppes before hee was able to ſubdue and caſte thoſe ſeuen wicked nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons but of the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d promiſed vnto the Iewes bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reſting vppon that ioyful and ſweete pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God, <hi>(As I was with Moſes ſo will I be with thee, I will not leaue thee nor forſake</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſu. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>thee)</hi> be vanquiſhed his enimyes, and placed Gods people in the lande of <hi>Chanaan. Gideon</hi> iudge of the Iſraelites; accompanyed with
<note place="margin">Gideon.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6973:42"/> three hundreth ſouldiers only went agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> mightie army of the <hi>Madianites, Amelechites</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iudie. 7.</note> and other eaſterne people, who came into the land of Iſrael with their Tentes as thicke as Greſhoppers in multitude, ſo that they and their Cammelles were without number: hee vanquiſhed them and put them to flight, for the ſpirite of the Lorde came vpon him, and he beleued the word of the Lord promiſing him victorye. <hi>Daniel</hi> by the malice and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny of the <note place="margin">Daniel.</note> Courtiers was caſt into the Lyons denne, yet through gods protection he was preſerued ſafe and ſound, the reaſon is expreſſed in the Text, <hi>Bicauſe he truſted in his God:</hi> whereat the Kyng wonderyng and reioyſing, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Daniell</hi> hys accuſers, their wyues and
<note place="margin">Daniel. 6.</note> children to bee put in his place, and the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons had the maiſtery ouer them, and brake all their bones in peeces or euer they came at the ground of their denne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> entyrely beloued of God, elected ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng <note place="margin">1. <hi>Samu.</hi> 16 2. Sa. 2. &amp;. 5.</note> to Gods owne hearte, and thryce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted Kyng of Iſraell, ledde yet a lyfe full of many miſeries and calamities, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note place="margin">Dauid.</note> of his wife <hi>Micholl,</hi> for that hee ſeemed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> precyſe in the obſeruyng of Ceremonies. Saul conceyued deadly feude agaynſt him, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6973:42"/> often ſought to kill him. <hi>Abſolon</hi> his owne ſonne defyleth his bedde, and rebelleth againſt him. Beſides this, what aſſaultes ſuſteyned he the Phyliſtines, the <hi>Moabites,</hi> the <hi>Syrians,</hi> the <hi>Idumites,</hi> great and mightie nations: yet hee is patiente in hys houſe, conſtante in hys Kyngdome, and victorious agaynſt ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ngers. For the almightie was his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, hys hope, and hys Protectour: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was vnpoſſible for hym to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded and deſtroyed. Which for that hee approued paſſyng all humayne expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, bee ſingeth after this manner: In thee O Lorde haue I put my truſte, lette mee <note place="margin">Pſal. 31.</note> neuer bee confounded, delyuer mee in thy righteouſneſſe: I will bee gladde and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in thy mercye, for thou haſte ſeene my trouble, and thou baſte knowne my ſoule in aduerſityes: And thou haſte not ſhutte met vppe in the hande of the enimye, but haſte ſet my feete at large. <hi>Aſa</hi> Kyng of <hi>Iuda,</hi> abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated <note place="margin">Aſa.</note> horrible Idolatrie and ſuperſtition, and commaunded <hi>Iudah</hi> to ſeeke the Lord God of
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Para.</hi> 14.</note> their fathers, &amp; to do according to do according to his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and be tooke away out of at the Cittes of <hi>Iuda</hi> the high places &amp; the images: therefore the kingdome was quiet before him, hee built
<pb facs="tcp:6973:43"/> ſtronge Cities in <hi>Iuda,</hi> and hee had no warre many yeares, bicauſe the Lord gaue him reſt. Afterward there came agaynſt him <hi>Zerach</hi> of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> with an hoſte of ten hundreth thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, and three hundreth Chariots. Then <hi>Aſa</hi> went out before him and ſet the battayle in aray, and cryed vnto the Lord his God, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Lorde it is nothing with thee to helpe with many, or with no power:</hi> helpe vs O lord our God, for wee reſte on thee, and in thy name we come againſt this multitude: O lord thou arte our God, let not many preuayle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt thee. So the Lord ſmote the <hi>Ethiopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> before <hi>Iudah</hi> and they fled, and the men of <hi>Iudah,</hi> caryed away a mightie great ſpoyle, and returned to <hi>Ieruſalem. Ioſaphat</hi> folowed <note place="margin">Ioſophat.</note> his father <hi>Aſa</hi> in clenſing the temple, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming true religion: he ſet Leuites in <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Para. 17. and 19.</note> for the iudgement of the cauſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord: and he appointed Iudges in the land through out the ſtrong Cities, &amp; ſayd vnto them, <hi>Take heed what ye do,</hi> for ye execute not the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of man but of the Lorde: and there is no iniquitie with the Lorde our God, neither reſpecte of perſons, nor receyuing of reward. Wherefore the Lord ſtabliſhed the kingdom in his hande, and the feare of the Lord fel vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6973:43"/> all the kingdomes of the lands that were rounde about <hi>Iudah,</hi> and they durſt not fighte agaynſt him, and ſtraungers brought <hi>Iehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> preſentes and giftes, and the <hi>Arabians</hi> brought him flocks of ſheepe and Goates, and hee proſpered and grewe vp an high, and his kingdome floriſhed exceedingly. <hi>Amaſias</hi> the
<note place="margin">Amaſias.</note> xij. King of <hi>Iuda</hi> hauing warre with the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Seer,</hi> hyred one hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to help him in battaile, but a man of god <note place="margin">2. Para. 25.</note> came vnto him, ſaying, O King let not the army of <hi>Iſrael</hi> go with thee, for God hath po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to helpe thee, and to caſt downe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King returned thoſe men accordyng to the ſaying of the Prophet, &amp; with his owne people couragiouſly went to the Salt valey, and encountered with his enimyes and ſlewe ten thouſandes, and other ten thouſande dyd the children of <hi>Iuda</hi> take alyue, and caryed them to the toppe of a rock, and tumbled them downe headlong, and they all burſt to peeces.
<note place="margin">Ezechias. 2. Reg. 19. Ieſa. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>Ezechias</hi> the xvj. King of <hi>Iuda,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an earneſt zeale embraſed true religion: and ſo perfitlye ſerued the Lorde, that after him was none like vnto him among all the Kings of <hi>Iuda,</hi> ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were there any ſuche before him, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meruellouſly tempted and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6973:44"/> the huge &amp; mightie army of the <hi>Aſſyrians,</hi> and terrified w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the blaſphemous ſpeech of <hi>Rabſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> turned vnto y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Lord, went into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple, &amp; lay proſtrate &amp; ſayd, O Lord our God, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, ſaue thou vs out of their hands, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the kingdoms of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth may know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ô lord art only god: which prayer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde harke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto, &amp; anſwereth thus: Bicauſe thou haſt praied vnto me co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning <hi>Synachereb</hi> king of <hi>Aſhur,</hi> I will put my hooke into his noſtrels, &amp; my bridle into his lips, &amp; wil bring him back again y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame way he came: he ſhal not enter this citie, nor ſhoote an arrow there, nor come before it with ſhield, nor caſt a mount againſt it. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame night y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Angel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord went out, &amp; ſmote in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> campe of <hi>Aſhur</hi> an hundred foure ſcore &amp; fiue thouſand: &amp; when they roaſe early in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning, behold they were all dead <note place="margin">Synachereb</note> corpſes. So <hi>Synachereb</hi> King of <hi>Aſhur</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, &amp; returned to <hi>Niniuie.</hi> And as he was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple worſhipping of <hi>Niſroh</hi> his god, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dramelech</hi> &amp; <hi>Sharezer</hi> his ſonnes ſlew him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſword, &amp; they eſcaped into y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lande of <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat,</hi> and <hi>Eſarhaddon</hi> raigned in his ſteed.</p>
               <p>Out of theſe hiſtories I gather three obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, <note place="margin">Three notes or oh ſernations.</note> firſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly tempteth his choſen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ighty aduerſaries, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their faith may
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6973:44"/> be more perfit tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gold tried w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fire: Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <note place="margin">1. Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that if they ſtedfaſtly truſt in him he bleſſeth their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> treaſure &amp; riches, &amp; repleniſheth their land with great plenty of valiant ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: Thirdly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God wil not ſuffer the heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh people and irreligious nations to treade his children vnder their feete, but with ſmall powers confoundeth their ten hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes in the day of battayle. My firſt note <note place="margin">1 God temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with many eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes. King Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ſix, and queene E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth.</note> appereth plainly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raign of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> late <hi>Ioſias,</hi> and preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly in our <hi>Heſter,</hi> who laboring in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new building of Gods tiple, good lord what a nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſubtile and bloudy enimyes haue whet their teeth againſt this little Ilande on euery ſide? but let vs not be diſmaid, for al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſts in <hi>Europe</hi> adioyning to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Turk, are not able to come once to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> field with ten hundred thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as <hi>Zerach</hi> of <hi>Ethiopia</hi> did againſt <hi>Aſa:</hi> &amp; if they were able to paſſe that number, haue we not legions of Angels vnder Chriſt his ſtanderd againſt them? Secondly, <hi>Aſa</hi> and <note place="margin">2 God fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alms wher he is ſerued with many valiant warriers.</note> 
                  <hi>Amazia</hi> Kings of <hi>Iuda,</hi> fearing the liuing god, had vnder them a floriſhing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, &amp; wer able to make thre hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d fighting me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey of engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hath wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted no te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral bleſſings, ſince god bleſſed vs with his word &amp; goſpel: neither do any monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and
<pb facs="tcp:6973:45"/> chronicles of England make record of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">England populous and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of good ſouldiers.</note> able men at one tyme, as are now to bee founde in this little Eland. I haue hard it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of credible men, (who by commiſſion had authoritie to make a bewe of ſuch things) that in the Countie of <hi>Deuon</hi> only, there hath bin ſounde fourtie thouſand comely and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men for the ſield: ſo that if euery county in Englande doe matche the ſame according to their proportions, there is no doubt but out powers will eyther ſurmount or anſwere that lande whereof I ſpake afore, in number of warlyke men. Laſtly, bowſoeuer this little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion <note place="margin">3 God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry not by many ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</note> hath bin ſtored with men of warre here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, yet a ſmall handfull hath ouermatched a huge hoſte, and moſt commonly (if I terme it aright) a thinne Garryſon hath ſuppreſſed and ſurpriſed many &amp; mightie armies of their enimyes, as in Eoward the third his dayes at <note place="margin">The victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Engliſhe men at <hi>Creſsie. The battel of Poyters.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Creſſy,</hi> where xix. thouſand Engliſh men put to flight one hundred thouſande frenchmen, and ſlew xxx. thouſande: at Poyters wher the <hi>blacke</hi> Prince lauing but a wing of men in reſpect of their enimyis, tooke priſoners, Iohn the French King, Phillippe his ſonne, ſeuen Earles, beſides Barons and Knightes. That blacke Prince, as hiſtoryes declary, had
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6973:45"/> the courage and harte of a Lyon, they mighte <note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant faith of the black Prince.</note> aſwell haue commended in him the conſtante fayth and aſſured hope of a godly and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Captayne. For ſeeing his power ſo farre vnequall to his aduerſaryes, and his meyny halfe ſorowfull, hee vttered ſuche voyces, as all godly engliſhe Capitaynes in lyke caſe ought to expreſſe. Well ſyrs (ſayth hee) albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it we be but ſewe in regarde to the multitude of our enimyes: let vs not bee abaſhed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for the victory lyeth not in the multitude of the people, but where it pleaſeth almightie God to giue it. Therefore truſt in him, and take Engliſh mens hartes vnto you this day: for if God wil, this dayes victory ſhalbe ours: and if we dye, wee haue a good quarell. With which wordes he anymated and encouraged his ſouldyers. <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth hauing in all but xv. thouſand, diſcomfited the flower of <hi>France</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; zeale of <hi>Henry</hi> the fyft.</note> at the battayle <hi>Agincourte,</hi> where ſixe French men men were in the fielde agaynſt one Engliſhe man: and at the ende of the battayle the nobl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Henry</hi> cauſed a retraite to be blown, &amp; brought all his armye togither, willing them to gyue thankes to God, by whoſe almightie power they bad receyued that victory: and euery one kneeling down ſwng, <hi>Not vnto vs Lord, not</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 115.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6973:46"/> 
                  <hi>vnto vs, but vnto thy name giue the glorye &amp;c.</hi> So that it euidently appeareth, that thys noble Prince had a perfit fayth and truſte in <note place="margin">Flodden field.</note> the ayde of the lord, which heard his prayer and regarded his fayth, and miraculouſly in mercy gaue him victory. In the dayes of the King of famous memory <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, Kyng Iames of <hi>Scotlande</hi> the fourth, came into England with one hundred thouſande at the leaſt, as all hiſtories agree, &amp; <hi>Paulus Iouius</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<note place="margin">P. Iouius.</note> the malaparte confidence of Iames in his hoſte, that he thought himſelf able with ſpear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to holde vp heauen, if it had bin ſlydying: but behold xxvj. thouſand Engliſhe men en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countereth him, vanquiſheth his ſtrength, and ſlew the king with the moſt part of the nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of <hi>Scotla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> at <hi>Brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſton</hi> in <hi>Cheuiot.</hi> Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <note place="margin">Mouſele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough fielde.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> field foughte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at <hi>Mouſcleborough</hi> is freſh in moſt mens memory, where God puniſhed the periury of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scots, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the loſſe of xv. thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſoldiers, &amp; miraculouſly, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any great effuſion of engliſh bloud (for there periſhed not aboue one hundred on our ſide) gaue vnto our countreymen a tryumphant victory. Such ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples are plentie, but I haue choſen a fewe, giuing occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto noble men therby to fixe their hartes vppon Gods fatherly prouidence
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6973:46"/> in all their diſtreſſes, and to ſing with diuine <note place="margin">Pſa. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Dauid,</hi> The King is not ſaued by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of an hoſte, neither is the Gyant deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by great ſtrength. A horſe is a vayn thing and ſhall not deliuer any by hys ſtrength: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the eye of the Lorde is vppon them that feare him, and vppon them that truſt in his mercy, to deliuer their ſoules, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue them in famyne.</p>
               <p>And as God Defendeth good Princes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt <note place="margin">God neuer ſuffreth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels and traytonts vnpuniſhed <hi>Chore.</hi>
                  </note> ſoren enimyes, ſo doth he moſt ſeuere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew his wrath, and powre his borrible and ſharpe puniſhmentes vppon Rebelles and Traytors at home. <hi>Chore, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> rebelling agaynſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> were ſwalowed into the earth quicke, and periſhed with a new and horrible kynde of death. <hi>Abſolon</hi> rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng <note place="margin">2. Sa. 18. Abſolon.</note> agaynſt his father was put to flight by <hi>Dauid</hi> vis army, and ſeking to eſcape through the woods. as his mule ranne vnder a thicke oke, his heare was intangled in the boughes, and he taken vp betweene the heauen and the earth, and the mule that was vnder him we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t away, ſo Ioab the Captayne came and ranne him through wyth dartes. <hi>Sybas</hi> the ſonne <note place="margin">Sybas. 2. Pſa. 20.</note> of <hi>Bochrus</hi> conſpiryng agaynſt Kyng <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> had a wretched ende, his head <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of by the
<pb facs="tcp:6973:47"/> counſayle of a prudent woman in <hi>Abela,</hi> and the ſame was caſte ouer the walles to <hi>Ioab.</hi> The acte of <note place="margin">Gaall</note> the ſonne of <hi>Ebed</hi> is nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <note place="margin">Gaall.</note> who with a ſeditious oration ſtyrred the men of <hi>Sichem</hi> to diſobey <hi>Abimelech,</hi> beyng <note place="margin">Ind. 9.</note> in deede but a Tyrant, for hee monſtrouflye murdered about ſeuentie of his bretherne, yet God fauoured not that cauſe, but ſuffered <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimelech</hi> to vanquiſh thoſe Rebelles, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly to ſubuert then Citie. The enterpriſe of the children of <hi>Ephraim</hi> againſt good <hi>Iephthe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ephraim. Iud. 12.</note> had lyke euent, for there fell of them by the handes of <hi>Gylead</hi> two and fourtie thouſand. <note place="margin">Theudas Gaulonites. Act. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Theudas Gaulonites</hi> made a ſhewe of earneſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eale and loue to deliuer his countreye from ſeruitude: and therefore by his pleaſaunt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions allured many to arme themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt <note place="margin">Ioſeph. lib. 18. cap. 1.</note> the <hi>Romaynes,</hi> but he was ſlayne, and his folowers (as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> declared) were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percled and brought to nought. And in our owne countrey we may beholde the ſeditious dealings of <hi>VVatte Tyler, Iacke Strawe, Iohn</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Watte Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, Iacke Strawe. Anno. 4. Richard. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>VVall</hi> and others, who albeit they were fano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the moſte parte, and had an army of 60. thouſand men, yet being in their chiefe ruffe, Watte was ſlayne, and they lyke ſheepe ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>road. <hi>Thomas Flamocke</hi> and <hi>Mighell</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:6973:47"/> 
                  <hi>Ioſephe</hi> the blackeſmith, procured the Corniſh
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Michael Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> the blackſmith <hi>Anno. 12. Henry.</hi> 7.</note> men to rebel agaynſt their Prince, and aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſuch a company, that they aſtonied al good and faithfull ſubiectes: but their power was diſcomfited at Blackeheath, their chiefe Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the Lorde <hi>Audeley</hi> beheaded, <hi>Thomas Flamocke</hi> and <hi>Mychaell Ioſephe</hi> were draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, hanged, and quartered, and their quarters pitched on ſtakes, after the manner of Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, to warne others to beware of like crimes and offences.</p>
               <p>Fynally, the vnhappy inſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in the dayes <note place="margin">Rebellion in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in our time.</note> of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, of King <hi>Edward</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xt, and of our ſoueraigne Lady the Dueenes maieſtie, made vnder pretence of defending the faith and holye church, and of deliueryng the common wealth from oppreſſion, do with ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ruine of noble families, with ſauage ſpoil of goodly countreys, with dreadfull executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of couragious perſonages, paynt before all mennes eyes the hatefull hatred of almightie God agaynſt Rebelles and Traytors, and there withall doe ſhewe Gods fatherly proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in aſſiſting good Princes and noble men, being enuironed on euery ſyde with enimyes, and oppreſſed with extreme miſeries and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6973:48"/>
               <p>Notwithſtanding I graunt ſome ſpeciall <note place="margin">Why God permitteth godly prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates ſometyme to bee op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by Tyrants.</note> examples may bee founde repugnaunt to the premiſſes, and it commeth to paſſe now &amp; then that wicked and ſeditious perſons proſper and preuail, &amp; that good &amp; lawful magiſtrats decay &amp; periſh: which things haue wonderfully aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myndes of mortal men, &amp; moued them to think that eyther there is no God, or at the leaſt that there is no diuine prouidence at all ouer earthly things: for if ther were any effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual care, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſurely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world ſhuld go happely w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the godly, &amp; vnhappely with the vngodly. Such firy darts wound euen Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thus w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> themſelues: if almightie God do care for earthly creatures, and eſpecially for the church, why did godleſſe <hi>Cain</hi> kil godly. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel?</hi> &amp; why did y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> lecherous &amp; filthy ſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe clean &amp; chaſt <hi>Ioſephe?</hi> why was the holy prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> giuen into y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hands of cruel <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes? whi did not y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> pietie of religious <hi>Dauid</hi> touer him from ſo many ſtormes &amp; tempeſtes? why did God ſuffer y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſlinking Gote <hi>Herodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> to behead him than who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther was no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter amongſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonnes of women? why was y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> monſtrous Tyrant &amp; very froth of miſchiefe <hi>Nero</hi> ſuffred to murder thoſe two notable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſt &amp; tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pets of true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul? Marcus Cato</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tidings came vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Cicil,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great <hi>Pompei</hi> through fear
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6973:48"/> of Caeſar had forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Italy,</hi> he cryed out ſaying, O immortal Gods, how obſcure and variable are your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſolations in humayne affaires? For vnto this daye haue you fauored <hi>Pompei,</hi> not <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pompelus magnus</hi> doubtes of gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence.</note> ſo exactly miniſtring equitie and iuſtice, but now in defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon libertie and in a moſt iuſt cauſe of his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey you haue forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. <hi>Pompei</hi> himſelfe ſcaping y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſword in the fielde foughte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at <hi>Pharſalia,</hi> ſailed to <hi>Mytelene</hi> where <hi>Cornelia</hi> his wife made hir abode, &amp; repairing to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Philoſopher <hi>Cratippus,</hi> lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted much his aduerſitie, &amp; queſtioned whither ther were any prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at all. And now in <hi>France</hi> who ſeeth not poyſeners, trucebreakers, Tyrants &amp; blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit <note place="margin">Frenche Tyranny.</note> Papiſts to ttiumph again, obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>edulous ſubieus oppreſte, profeſſours of true religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> murdered, honorable gray whyte heads are cleft aſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> great bellies &amp; wombs of Ladies &amp; gentlewome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ripped, infantes and ſucking babes are w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> pykes perced, and fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, no kinde of crueltie vnpractiſed. Albeit, ſuch lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table calamities of good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage libertie of wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, both in churches &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welaths ſeeme to take away gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: yet god to remoue ſuch doubts, hath ſet before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s eyes, his workes ordinarie &amp; extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, &amp; hath added thereunto his expreſſe &amp; manifeſt word, thereby ſhewing the properity
<pb facs="tcp:6973:49"/> and aduerſitie come not to men by chance, but to be diſpoſed and diſtributed as it were with Gods hand. And touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proſperitie of the wicked, whom it pleaſeth God to aduance e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <note place="margin">Why God permitteth the wicked to proſper. <hi>Exo.</hi> 9.</note> vnto the higheſt ſteppe of honour and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, we haue the cauſe alleged by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, of <hi>Pharao,</hi> after this maner: For this cauſe haue I appoynted thee, to ſhewe my power in thee, and to declare my name throughout all the world. In this text God expreſſeth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that of his owne purpoſe &amp; will he anaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and obdured <hi>Pharao:</hi> which his will hee proueth good and iuſt, by two reaſons: Fyrſt to ſhewe his iuſtice and power, ſecondarily, that his name might be renoumed throughout the whole worlde: which two things had bin hidden hidden tyme, if <hi>Pharao</hi> his ſtrength and power had not bin famous among the nations round about: and therefore that new and ſtraunge puniſhement in drownyng ſo mightie an armye of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> in the red Sea, and in ſauing his own ſimple and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed people the Iſraelits, did note the ſame. The wicked then clyme alofte by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyntment, that their great and beauye ruyne may bee more apparant: and their worldlye honour and glory is notable, that their ſhame
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6973:49"/> and diſhonor may be more notable. Whereof <note place="margin">The fall of Tirantes.</note> beſſdes <hi>Pharao</hi> of <hi>Egypt, Nabuchodonozer</hi> of <hi>Babylon, Chuſan</hi> of Meſopotamia, Eglon</hi> of <hi>Moab, Synacherib</hi> of <hi>Aſſyria, Edward</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and <hi>Richarde</hi> the thirde of <hi>Englande</hi> do yeld vnto vs firme proofe and playne declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo that the moſt mighty Empires of the world haue their exaltation and declination: and Tyrants haue their fall, and are puniſhed for their riottouſneſſe, pride, oppreſſion, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of innocent bloud, euen by the hands of bloudy men: and one wicked ſucceedyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in a long tract and courſe of time, doe murther one another: vntill at laſt, the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire come vnto one vertuous Prince, who with much a doe dieth naturally in his bedde. The Chroniles of England, make large me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in this land, betweene the Kings of the <hi>Saxons</hi> and <hi>Danes,</hi> from the raigne of <hi>Brithricus,</hi> vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of <hi>Swainus,</hi> by the tearme of 255. yeeres. And who can be ignorant (that hathe but a little turned ouer our countrey hiſtories) of a heape of ſuch Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall examples from <hi>Edward</hi> the third vnto <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth by the ſpace of one hundred <note place="margin">Tirants dye ſeldome a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall death.</note> and fiue yeeres. And if one Tyrante oppreſſe not another, which moſt commonly commeth
<pb facs="tcp:6973:50"/> to paſſe, according to the Poet,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ad generu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cere is, ſine cade &amp; ſanguine pauci</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi> Deſcendunt reges, &amp; ſicca morte Tyranni.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Then God ſendeth eyther his deſtroying Angell, which happened to <hi>Senacherib, Herod</hi> and <hi>Iulian,</hi> or ſharpneth their owne daggers, whiche came to paſſe in <hi>Saul, Zamry</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod.</hi> Wherfore let good Princes put their affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in God, who alone is able to turne Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies into Comedies, ſorowe into ioy, and take away the ſtormes of calamitie, and ſhine vpon vs with the beames of proſperitie. God knoweth beſt what is expediente for vs, and how long it is profitable for his people to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in miſerie and thraldome, in <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babilon.</hi> He alone hath in his hand the hartes of Kings, and he it is that hardneth <hi>Pharao,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all welfare of wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this world a ſigne of more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Senacherib, Holofernes,</hi> and againe, that mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifieth <hi>Cyrus, Nabuchodonozer</hi> and <hi>Aſſuerus.</hi> And if God ſuffer wicked Tyrants with qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe and peace to deſcend vnto their graue, as he ſuffered the rich glutton, of whome wee reade in the Goſpell. It is an euident argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that ſuch one is reſerued vnto the paines of the world to come, whiche neuer ſhall haue <note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> end, wher weeping and gnaſhing of teeth ſhal be, as we ſee it chanced to the foreſaid glutton,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:6973:50"/> vnto whom God ſaid, Sonne, remember tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> than in thy life time receyuedſt thy pleaſure; &amp; contrariwiſe <hi>Lazarus</hi> receiued payne, but now <note place="margin">Hebr. 12.</note> be is comforted and thou art puniſhed. The holy Apoſtle ſaith, What ſon is he whome the father chaſtiſeth not? If ye be not vnder cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection (whereof all are partakers) then are yee baſtards and not ſonnes. A terrible end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore abideth them, which in this world licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auſly &amp; without puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t do ſinne, for al ſuch be baſtrads &amp; not ſonnes, therfore haue they no <note place="margin">Sapi. 2.</note> part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly inherit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce: And thoſe vol volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Epirures, whiche in this worlde ſaye. Come &amp; let vs enioy the pleaſures y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are, &amp; le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vs ſome vſe the creature, like as in youth. Let vs fil our ſelues with good wine &amp; pyntment, &amp; let there no flour of time goe by vs. Let vs crown our ſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> roſes, before they be withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Let there be no faire medow but our luſt go through it. Let euery one of you be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of our voluptuouſnes. Let vs leaue ſome toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of pleaſur in euery place, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is our por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, elſe get we nothing. &amp;c. But ſuch in time to come ſhal crie out in this maner &amp; ſay, We <note place="margin">Sapi. 6.</note> haue erted from the way of trueth, the lyghte of ryghteouſneſſe hathe not ſhined vppon vs, Wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aue wearied our ſelues in the way of
<pb facs="tcp:6973:51"/> wickedneſſe and diſtruction. Tedious wayes haue we gone, but as for the way of the Lord we haue not knowen it &amp;c. Such words ſhall they that haue ſinned, ſpeake in the Hell. For the hope of the vngodly is like a dri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Thiſtill flower, that is blowen away with the winde. The felicitie of the vngodly therefore in thys life, is extreame miſerie, and a ſigne of theyr <note place="margin">A worthy hiſtorie of <hi>polycrates. Strabo. lib.</hi> 14.</note> heauie gretuous puniſhment in hell torments. The C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>huikes alſo donbted the ende of ſuche men ad continued long in greate proſperitie, and affirmed ſome vnhappie end to enſue, as <hi>Amaſis</hi> writ to <hi>Polycrates.</hi> This <hi>Polycrates</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Sabell. Eneid. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> was chiefe gouernour of <hi>Samus,</hi> who was ſo happie in all his life, that hee ſeemed to be the very ſonne and heire of good fortune. For hee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſting of purpoſe into the Sea a ring moſt excellently wrought, wherein was ſet (as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dotus</hi> writeth) a Smargde, but <hi>Plinie</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it a <hi>Sardonichem,</hi> precious ſtones of no
<note place="margin">Plinius natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralis hiſto. li. 23. cap. 1.</note> ſhall price, minding as ſome coniecture, with that greate loſſe to preuente and anoyde miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune: It chaunced within fiue dayes after, a fiſher to take a goodly great fiſhe, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Amaſis</hi> King of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
                  </note> bought for the King, and brought to the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> to be br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſed, behold in the drawing, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ng was founde in the bellie of the fiſhe, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6973:51"/> was broughte out of hande to <hi>Poly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="6 letters">
                        <desc>••••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Whereof when <hi>Amaſis.</hi> king of <hi>Egypt</hi> had<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the ſaid king his letters, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered againe to <hi>Polycrates</hi> largely, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayling mans ſlipp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> of that, among <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> things, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this deuine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as <hi>leade their life in thes world<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> all felicitie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>do end their life in great miſerie.</hi> Whiche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in deede in <hi>Polycrates.</hi> For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>nded by the policie of a King of the <hi>Perſons,</hi> and being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> abuſed, was in the end moſt ſhamefully hanged. Herevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to agreeth that hiſtorie of S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who <note place="margin">
                     <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> his iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of continuall proſperitie.</note> trau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Rome, by the way wente <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> rich mans houſE to lodge, and in his inter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ment, there fell out commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of the rich mans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ate, who ioyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> leſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſtingly anſwrred: The worlde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fid wned vppon me, but all things haue come to me euen according to my hartes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire. Which wordes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that woithy Biſhop heard, he ſpake vnto his company and ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Away hence ſins with all ſpeade, God loueth not this houſe, he hath no manſion here. And ſee the ſequele: They were not gone farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, hifore the earth ſuddainely opened, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vp the man with all that eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:6973:52"/> he had, ſo that nothing was ſaued, both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> are, that God is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeut, where the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was abſent, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in firme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, where God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. For Saint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Apoſtle ſayth: Ye haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and in wantonueſſe, you haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in a day of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> yt haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> killed the iuſti, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Iames. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere. 12.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>O Lord if I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with thee of thy.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the may of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> they in wealth, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> haſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ted the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; they haue taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in their mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; far <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their mints, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lord pull them, out like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them for the day of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Mala. 4.</note> is greate diffedence in the days of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iuſt, ſpeaking after this manner: For beholde the day conu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th that ſhall burne as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and all that do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſhall he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the day that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6973:52"/> ſayth the Lorde of hoſts, and ſhall leaue then<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> neyther oote, neither braunche, but vnto you that feare my name, ſhall the ſunne of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ariſe, and healthe ſhall be vnder hys wings, and yee ſhall goe foorthe and growt vp as fat Calues. Let no good man thereforeſtumble at the proſperitie of the vngodly, let them not ſeeke to haue any part of the vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie portion of the wicked. Sith that as Dauid writeth. In the hande of the Lord there is a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and the wine is red, it is full mixt, and he powreth out of the ſame, ſurely all the wicked <note place="margin">Pſal. 75.</note> of the earthe ſhall wring out and drinke the dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gges thereof.</p>
               <p>Nowe as ſome wicked and bloudy Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants <note place="margin">Examples of godly Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed. 2. reg. 12.</note> proſper and come vnto a quiet ende, ſo ſome good Princes and magiſtrates are affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and cruelly murthered. Good <hi>Ionathas</hi> is ſlaine of the Philiſtines. <hi>Iehoas</hi> King of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> walking in the wayes of the Lord, is tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly inurthered by his owne ſeruants. <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> vnto whome no king of <hi>Iuda</hi> eyther be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him or after him, mighte be compared in <note place="margin">2. Reg. 23.</note> ſincereneſſe of hart and holineſſe of life, was ſlayne by wicked <hi>Pharao Necho</hi> king of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> at <hi>Megiddo.</hi> And if we conſider our own ſtories, wee ſhall reade of King <hi>Alu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> who <note place="margin">Alured.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6973:53"/> was indued with great knowledge in al lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as well prophane as deuine of feruente zeale, and of a vertuous and godly life, yet hee beeing oppreſſed with more number of eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies than any other did leade an vncertayne, troubleſome and vnquiet life, and forſaken of his friends, wandered in the wood countrey of Sommerſet ſhire, and had ſkant to liue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all. King <hi>Iohn</hi> ſtudying to repreſſe the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh <note place="margin">King <hi>Iohn.</hi>
                  </note> Tyrannie in England, and to reduce the true knowledge of God, was poyſoned by <hi>Simon</hi> a Monke of <hi>Swinſteed.</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">King <hi>Henry.</hi>
                  </note> the ſixt, ſurnamed the Saint, for that ther was in him all vertues, and a ſpeciall ſtudie for the health of his ſoule, the ſauing wherof be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be the greateſt wiſedome, and the loſſe thereof the extremeſt follie, yet was he tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly murthered in the Towre by <hi>Richard</hi> Duke of <hi>Gloceſter.</hi> And euen nowe the moſt trayterous, lamentable and cruell murder of <note place="margin">French Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie.</note> many thouſand of Chriſtes me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers in <hi>France,</hi> aſwell high and lowe, men, women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, doth preache vnto vs Gods wonderfull diſpenſation in puniſhing his Church. Albeit the cauſes of theſe calamities are many, yet I will not throughly proſecute them, being not ſo pettinent to my purpoſe, but will contente
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6973:53"/> my ſelfe with that whiche ſeemeth to mee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt to bee moſte comfortable: namely, that they are ſignes and tokens of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie and of eternall felicitie. For ſeeing God hathe promiſed to his children all good things, and permitteth the vngodly to oppreſſe them: notwithſtanding he confirmeth by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert and euidente witneſſe, that hee alloweth and approueth <hi>Iohn Baptiſt, Paule</hi> and ſuche like. It conſequently followeth, another time and place to remayne, when <hi>Iohn</hi> and <hi>Paule</hi> ſhall be comforted: <hi>Herode</hi> and <hi>Nero</hi> puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, according to the ſaying of <hi>Peter,</hi> The <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> tyme is come, that iudgemente muſt begin at the houſe of God. If it firſt begin at vs, what ſhall the ende be of them whiche obey not the Goſpel of God? Gods choſen and electe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren therefore are afflicted in this life, by gods peculiar counſayle. And againe, the wicked ſeeme to be bleſſed in this world, but the electe haue no portion in this worlde, nor the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate in the world to come. Yet doth not God alwayes ſuffer his children to grone vnder the yoke of affliction, but comforteth and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſheth them (as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſayth) God is angry indeede, when he ſeemeth not to be angry: and <note place="margin">The godly moſt perfit in ſorowe.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi> As golde reteyneth ſtill his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour
<pb facs="tcp:6973:54"/> and brightneſſe both in water and fire: but Hay and Strawe runne abroade in the water, and are conſumed with the fire. Euen ſo fareth it with the godly and the vngodly, for when the godly are in proſperitie, they are as golde in the water, in aduerſitie, they are more brighte and beautifull, as golde in the fire. And againe, the wicked being in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, are ſcattered abroade like water: &amp; in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie they periſh as Hay in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fornace. Now if God do any long ſpace trie vs in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtormes of miſerie &amp; calamitie, whereas he is able euery moment to releeue vs, yet doth it not before he perceiueth vs purified and prepared to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. For as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goldſmith taketh not his golde out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fornace, before it be exactly tried &amp; cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the droſſe, ſo doth not god take his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fornace of afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, before he ſeth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> clenſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> groſe affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and carnal appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, &amp; wholly bent to newnes &amp; holines of life.</p>
               <p>If then Princes &amp; noble men do taſt at any <note place="margin">Princes ought to call vpon God in their diſtreſſe and not to deſpaire of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> help.</note> time of miſeries and calamities, they oughte patiently to ſuffer the ſame, ſeeing that they are Gods chaſtiſement and correction, ſeruing to their better perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And moreouer, in the middle of their troubles, they are taught by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> examples of good and godly princes to flee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6973:54"/> the liuing God, by ardente inuocation &amp; prayer: both for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> there is no danger ſo greate out of the whiche God is not able to deliuer them. And again, no accombrance, be it neuer ſo light &amp; ſmal, out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they are able to wind themſelues, vnleſſe God with a ſpeciall care &amp; prouidence put too his helping hand. It then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prince or magiſtrate his owne perſon, be in danger of death through ſome greeuous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>heſſe: let him call to his remembrance the example of <hi>Ezechias,</hi> let him ſettle his hope in
<note place="margin">Examples of Gods deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching princes and noble men princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally.</note> God, let him bewayle his ſinnes with bitter teares, &amp; God will ſende ſome <hi>Eſaias</hi> who ſhal adminiſter vnto him comfort, and ſalue for his greeuous ſore. If a plage and Peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his people aſtone him; let him folow king <hi>Dauid,</hi> &amp; offer for his people y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifices of an humble &amp; lowly hart, &amp; ther is no doubt, but the conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming peſtilence ſhal ceaſſe. If famine and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurie may which thee can almoſt be no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter miſerie do affect his land, let him endeuor to get ſome prouident <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> to releeue the deere yeeres of <hi>Egypt</hi> in his countrey. If the earth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and become barraine, let him call vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, &amp; ſome <hi>Elias</hi> by his prayers wil open y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauens to ſend downe their moiſture, or ſome <hi>Elizeus,</hi> who wil ſhew vnto <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>am</hi> &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:6973:55"/> 
                  <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> whole riuers of water to releeue them. If ſworde and fire in wars doe make him tremble, or if in the day of battell be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire of victorie, let him recorde with hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that it, lieth in Gods hande, to reſkew him and his men, and to reſcue him with good <hi>Ezechias,</hi> who with prayer preuayled more than <hi>Sennacherib</hi> with his hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands. If it pleaſe God to throwe him into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riles, or into captiuitie, he may not for al this deſpaire, but with <hi>Manaſſes</hi> turning vnto the Lord, let him hope to be deliuered out of the dungeon in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and to ſee his Citie <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> againe. If his people rebell on euery ſide, <hi>Dauid</hi> teacheth him to ſay, <hi>The Lords wil be done.</hi> Yet in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> meane time he ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire God to infatuate the deuiſes of his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarſaries, and God will appoint ſome fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Chuſu</hi> to bring to nought, the counſayls of tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iterous <hi>Achitophell,</hi> and will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſſe by ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſalon.</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> which tribulation being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> other moſt greeuous) as <hi>David</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> when he ſaw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> murther: yet if he re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, God will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Nathan</hi> to ereſte and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6973:55"/> comfort him. And finally, what tribulation ſoeuer the magiſtrate taſt of, whether it be ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituall or corporall, publike or priuate: let him make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liuing God his ſhooteanker, and looke for conſolation and comfort at his hand.</p>
               <p>Nowe if they thus cleaue vnto almightie <note place="margin">Why God doth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants from painful deths</note> God, let them not doubt, but he will ſuccoure and deliuer, if not the fleſhe, yet the ſpirite: if not their bodies yet, certainely, he will not permit their Soule to periſh: for that GOD whiche deliuered the three children out of the fierie fornace, and <hi>Daniel</hi> out of the Lions denne, ſuffered the <hi>Machabees, Vincentius,</hi> and infinite Martires, to die in ſharp tormentes, and yet he is the God of the one and of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. He therefore ſaueth ſome miraculouſly, to confound Idolatrie: he permitteth otherſome to periſh in their bodies, that the ſtrong paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Martirs may be ſeene, and that the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the vngodly may be the heauier in <note place="margin">Auguſt. pſa. 33.</note> Hell fire. When <hi>Vincentius</hi> was rent and al to torne vppon the racke, and after caſt vppon <note place="margin">Vincentius.</note> the hote coales, he ſpake to the Tirant <hi>Dacia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> Shew all furor and crueltie vpon me that <note place="margin">Bergomenſis in ſupple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento.</note> thou art able, by Gods power, I ſhall bee more firme and patient in ſuffering, than thou in afflicting. Whence came ſuch courage and
<pb facs="tcp:6973:56"/> boldneſſe? Surely all the cogitations of the godly men, are ſettled vppon the rocke, the ſonne of God. Without him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godlye would ſhrinke euen into the quagmire of deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but knowing their cauſe, they lift vp theyr heads and march after their Captayne Ieſus Chriſt. And being armed with the ſhielde of faith, whereby they haue an aſſured eſtate in the life to come, they force not much what may <note place="margin">Examples of good men, not dying natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally in theyr beddes.</note> come to their mortall bodies, neither doe they thinke it a miſerable ende, if they die with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſword, in the fire, vpon the gallowes, or by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other wayes, ſo it be for the name of the Lord Ieſus. And if wee conſider examples, it will euidently appeare, that many of Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect died not in their beds a naturall death. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel</hi> was murthered of his owne brother. The Prophet beeing ſente to <hi>Hieroboam,</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by a Lyon. <hi>Eſay</hi> was ſawen aſunder through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mids. <hi>Ieremy,</hi> like as <hi>Stephen</hi> alſo, was ſtoned to death. <hi>Iames</hi> being throwen downe from the Pinacle of the temple, was <note place="margin">Heb. 11.</note> ſlayn of a fuller. <hi>Peter</hi> was faſtried to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> croſſe <hi>Paul</hi> was executed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſword. Many ſuch examples are extant. Beſides theſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> famous men amongſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Heathen died miſerably tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. The good <hi>Socrates</hi> was poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, <hi>Euripides</hi> was forne with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phocles</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:6973:56"/> was choked with a berrie of a grape. Very ſorowfull cumbrance &amp; greefe of minde killed <hi>Homer.</hi> But <hi>Socrates</hi> accompted it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort <note place="margin">Socrates.</note> inough for good men to die innocently, &amp; for good deſerts to receyue vndeſerued puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Chriſts Apoſtles accord with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, who reioyced y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> they were found meete to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayne <note place="margin">Actes. 5.</note> contumelies for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: the reaſon is thus: If we be ſpoyled of our goodes in this world, we haue other treaſures in heauen: if we be here exiled, we are ther re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued into gods family: if we be murthered, a dore is opened vnto vs to euerlaſting lyfe. <note place="margin">To remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the day of iudgemente, eaſeth the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of the vngodly. <hi>Icza. 25. Reuela.</hi> 7.</note> wherfore let princes &amp; noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temne ſuch perils, &amp; tolerate ſuch croſſes, if it pleaſe god to lay the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſhoulders. Which thing they ſhalbe able to do, if they ſet before their eyes y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> day whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord will giue vnto his choſen a quiet kingdom, will wipe away al teares fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their eys, &amp; wil voutſafe to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> partakers of his euerlaſting kingdom. But as for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly which haue floriſhed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, he will throw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into vtter deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wher their ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ſhalbe reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>penced w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> payns, their laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> weping &amp; grinding of teeth, their peace ſhalbe vnquieted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the worme of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; they ſhal behold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly whome they haue perſecuted &amp; killed raigning ouer them in all
<pb facs="tcp:6973:57"/> bleſſedneſſe. For this is that iuſtice, whereof <note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 1.</note> the Apoſtle ſpeaketh, to eaſe thoſe that be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly afflicted, and to puniſh the oppreſſors of the godly, at that day when the Lorde Ieſus ſhall be reueled from heauen. This ſurely, ought to comfort, not only noble, but all chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian men: and this is their triumph ouer the world, the fleſh, the Diuell, and all his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, to fixe their hartes and mindes vpon the reſurrection: when the Lorde will poure vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his enimies fire and brimſtone, ſtorme, and tempeſt for their portion, and will crowne his owne children with glorie, honor and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie.</p>
               <trailer>Only vnto God be honor and glory.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:6973:57"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
